林氏王朝字幕組出品
微博地址：http://weibo.com/jl7ld
翻譯：奧利奧   遠遠的咕咕   大萌    回鍋肉JJYY    簡單計劃
校對：遠遠的咕咕   簡單計劃
後期效果：遠遠的咕咕
禁止將本字幕用於商業用途
轉載請註明 林氏王朝字幕組
當時已經是我到球隊後的第二還是第三場主場比賽了
Jeremy lin: So it was like my second or third home game,
我甚至還從未上過場
And I hadn't even been in a game yet,
當我試圖進入球館時
And I had tried to get in the gym,
他們攔住我
And they stopped me.
他們說
And they were like,
「抱歉，這裏是球員入口」
"oh, sorry, this is the players' entrance."
我說，「我知道啊」
I was like, "I know."
那個保安就困惑地看著我
He looked at me confused,
於是我也困惑地看著他
And then so I was looking at him confused.
然後他說
And then he was like,
「哦，抱歉，你是隊上的訓練師嗎？」
"oh, I'm sorry. Are you a trainer?"
我站在那不知道說什麼好
And I was just kind of just like standing there.
然後另一個保安走過來
And then another security guard came over
對著之前那個耳語道，「他應該是在隊上打球的」
And, like, whispered, "I think he plays on the team."
現在上場的是後衛...
At guard it's...
十七號，林書豪！
Number 17, jeremy lin!
書豪
Hey, jeremy.
Hi.
沒有人認為他會打球
Nobody thought he could play.
他需要為所得的一切而戰
He had to fight for everything that he got.
你很少能有這種感覺：你見證了
It's not often you think you've seen something
聯盟中罕見的奇跡
You couldn't possibly see in the nba.
林投籃！
Lin puts it up!
進了！
Bang!
等等，這小子是誰？
Wait a minute. Who's this kid?
等等，他從哪冒出來的？
Wait. Where's he from?
等等，落選秀？
Wait. Not drafted?
等等，被多少球隊裁掉過？
Wait. How many teams waived him?
當他打球時
When this guy is playing,
勇士隊不知道他這麼棒
And golden state doesn't know he's any good,
火箭隊不知道他這麼棒
Houston doesn't know he's any good,
我不得不想，難道是因為
I got to imagine that something has to do with
他看上去不像個打球的好手
He doesn't look the part.
林書豪從默默無聞走到偉大
Jeremy lin came from nothing to greatness.
嘿，這小子給所有孩子以希望
Hey, this kid is giving hope to all those kids
那些認為自己永遠不會有機會的孩子
That think, "never could I have a chance."
我一直對自己說，我的進步歷程會是這樣
I always told myself my progression is gonna be
從進入輪換，到成為首發控衛
Become a rotation player, become a starting point guard,
然後贏得NBA總冠軍
And then win an nba championship.
人們聽到後肯定會嘲笑我
And people are definitely gonna laugh when they hear that.
但是有朝一日這一切成真時
You know, they're not gonna be laughing
他們就不會再笑了
If it actually happens.
新澤西網隊
對
紐約尼克斯
2012年2月4日
48個小時內，林書豪就會被裁掉
很可能就此終結他的NBA事業
並結束他的一生夢想
防守！
De-fense!
尼克斯隊的山姆波特，個人第二次犯規
New york foul is on shumpert, his second.
現在他得下場休息會兒了
And now, he'll have to take a seat,
看看誰要上場了
And, again, mike, look who's coming in.
是林書豪，你可以聽到球迷的大聲歡呼
Jeremy lin, and you hear a pretty big ovation.
我知道是神在安排這一切
Jeremy: I know god orchestrated this whole thing.
因為太多事情在我的掌控之外
There's just too much out of my control.
而且它們發生的方式是那樣的不可思議
And just the way it happened is just miraculous.
書豪！
Jeremy!
是真的
It's actually true.
在我大概八、九歲後
After, I think, age maybe 8 or 9,
我們換掉了電視
We got rid of the tv,
我們會在季後賽時看比賽
And we would just get it during the playoffs.
我們會在家看
We would watch it in the house
然後在後院
And then, in the backyard,
有扇玻璃門，外面有個籃筐
There's a glass door and a hoop outside,
我們會在外面透過窗子看
So we would just watch through the window,
然後在場間休息或是暫停時
And then any time there was,like, a break or a time-out,
我們會出去模仿
We'd go out, and we'd do the exact move
剛剛球場上出現過的動作
That just happened.
基本上就全部都是模仿喬丹
And it was pretty much all just copying michael jordan
並且看到他取得勝利
And watching him win.
我們熱愛那種觀看比賽的方式
And so we loved watching basketball that way,
那一直是我的一個夢想
And it was always a dream of mine,
但我從未想過它會變成現實
But I didn't actually think it would be a reality.
你在哪搞到這個的？
Where did you get this done?
在市中心
是嗎？在格林威治村？
Down town.
Oh, yeah? Down in the village?
來看看這個
Can you take a look? Look at this.
讓我看看..背上這是..
Let me see what you... This is the back of...
怎麼樣？
What do you think?
非常棒
Beautifully done.
Yeah.
無與林比
Lintastic.
謝謝
Thank you.
所有孩子都有自己的夢想
Every kid has a dream.
有些想當消防員，有些想當宇航員
Some want to be a fireman, others an astronaut.
大多數時候，夢想只是夢而已
Most of the time, dreams are just dreams.
這個夢始於加州帕羅奧托
This dream starts in palo alto, california,
舊金山的一片郊區
A suburb of san francisco,
在這裏，一個年輕人學習信仰
Where a young man learns about faith,
堅韌與機遇
Perseverance, and opportunity.
茄子！
Cheese!
在台灣，我們只重視學習，我們並不重視打球
林明傑
林書豪的爸爸
那時候上完班之後，每次就很累，覺得很累
我在想說，我看籃球看了這麼多，特別是NBA
那我就開始練習打籃球
我自己練習了五年，像怎麼運球，怎麼投籃
怎麼上籃，我自己練了五年各式各樣的
而且我特別喜歡練習的就是賈巴爾的勾手
我如果有小孩子
在他們小時候一定要開始
帶他們一起打籃球
當爸爸帶我們去基督教青年會打球時
Joshua lin: My dad was taking us to the ymca.
我們還在上小學
We were still, like, in elementary school.
週一、三、五球館開放
There's like open gym Monday,Wednesday, fridays,
林書雅
林書豪的哥哥
從晚上七點半到九點半
From like 7:30 to 9:30.
當時我們放學回家後
And we would just come home from school,
我們會盡快做完作業
And we would just all do our homework as fast as possible.
當有人不能完成作業時
And then when someone couldn't finish their assignment,
我們會互相幫助
Then we would go and help them,
如果我做不完
So if I couldn't finish,
我哥就會來幫我
Josh would come over and help me.
如果弟弟做不完
If joe couldn't finish,
我們就會去幫他
You know, we would go over and help joe.
這是我們一直學到的一點
That's everything we've always known is just, you know,
就是我們是兄弟，我們是彼此最好的朋友
Having each other and being best friends with each other.
我當時不喜歡彈鋼琴
I didn't want to play the piano,
我彈得很糟
And I was horrible at the piano.
每年的表演會上
Like, every year,the recital would come around,
我都會彈同一首曲子
And I'd be pretty much playing the same song.
我的父母就覺得這樣不行
And they were just like, "this is not working.
完全是在浪費錢
"I'm wasting my money.
這孩子只愛打籃球
"all he does is play basketball,
那就讓他打籃球吧
So let's just let him play basketball."
當我們逐漸愛上這項運動時
As we grew to love the game,
我媽媽給予了巨大支持
My mom becamea huge supporter.
我想她能看出我們是真愛籃球
I think she could just see that we loved basketball,
看出我們心中的熱愛與激情
That we were passionate about it.
而她全心愛著我們
And she's passionate about us
所以無論我們想做什麼
So whatever we wanted to do,
她總是願意支持我們
She always wanted to support us.
她總是開車送大家，她是全隊的家長
She always drove. She was always a team parent
在所有二哥和我打過的
For every njb, aau
林書偉
林書豪的弟弟
全國青少年籃球聯賽（NJB）和
業餘體育聯盟比賽（AAU）
That jeremy played for, that I played for.
她總會出現在左右
She was always there.
支持著我們
She was always supporting us.
不是所有的母親，尤其是亞裔母親
You know, not every mom, asian mom especially,
會支持孩子打籃球
Is gonna support their child playing basketball.
Cheese!
Hi!
堅強的意志
Strong will.
堅強的意志?
Strong will?
堅強的意志
Strong will.
如果他想要什麼東西
If he wants something,
他會竭盡所能去得到
He will do anything to get that thing.
他會把頭往地上撞
So he will knock his head on the ground.
他會故意摔倒
He will just make himself fall.
他會做一切事情來試圖得到自己想要的東西
He will do anything to get what he wants.
在我成長過程中，我的家庭總是強調神是首位的
Growing up, my family always emphasized god first,
學業其次，運動第三
School second, athletics third.
剛開始，他們並不確定
In the beginning, they weren't sure
我能打多久的籃球
How long I could play basketball.
他們就是決定順其自然
They were just gonna ride it out
盡可能地享受籃球帶來的快樂
And have fun with it as long as we could.
我當時受邀前往一場
帕羅奧托的基督教青年會聯賽
Jim sutter: I got invited to a y league game in palo alto.
他當時就是一個小小孩
And he's just this little kid.
吉姆· 薩特
AAU球隊METRO MIRAGE的教練
你不會想到
You know, you wouldn't think it,
他的得分能力這麼出色
But he just scored the basketball so well.
第一場比賽時
The first tournament we played,
他開始狂投三分
And he just starts just raining 3-pointers.
Yeah!
他們說我叫得太大聲了
They will say I am so loud,
因為我會不停喊「防守！」
Because I will keep talking, "defense!"
或是「搶籃板！」
You know, "get a rebound!"
Yeah!
當然他媽媽當時會那樣
Of course, mom's like,
不停喊「他得了多少分？」
"how many points
did he score?"
她會說，「我告訴過你他棒極了吧」
She'd say, "I told you he was pretty good."
我會說，「我知道，我知道他很棒」
I go, "I know. I know he's pretty good."
當時所有AAU的球隊都不要書豪
All the aau team, they never want jeremy,
即便他是當時最棒的控衛
Even though he's the best point guard at that time.
只有這一支球隊
Only this particular aau,
Metro Mirage非常想要書豪為他們打球
Metro mirage, want him so bad.
耶，書豪！
Yeah, jeremy!
我喜歡處在這個被輕視的位置
I love being the underdog
因為這是我習慣的角色
Just because it's just what I'm used to.
也許我在聯盟中會打得不錯
You know, I would be good in this league,
但人們會說
And then people would say,
「但是他在這個聯盟中不可能打好的」
"oh, but he can't play well in this league."
每次書豪對位某個人們都說棒的球員
Every time jeremy play against somebody who people say is good,
如果書豪打得更好
If jeremy played better,
他們就會開始想，其實是這人不行
Then they start thinking, "that person's not good."
而不會肯定書豪打得好
They don't give jeremy credit.
有一種十四塊錢的超大玉米餅
There's a $14 extra-large burrito
就像這麼大
That's like this.
我的天，你一定得買那個吃
Oh, my gosh, you should totally get that.
書豪，你要買這個大的嗎？
Jeremy, you gonna get the big one?
是的
Jeremy: Yeah.
人與食物大對決
Man versus food.
我要開啟野獸模式了
I'm about to beast this.
我也不知道我是怎麼長這麼高的
Jeremy: I don't know how I got so tall, dude.
我食量很大
I ate a lot.
我會去吊單杠
I would hang
from monkey bars.
我會躺在床沿想著
Um, I would lie off the edge of my bed thinking
重力會把我拉長
That gravity would pull me and make me taller.
當我高一時我只有一米六左右
When I was 5'3" as a freshman in high school,
我記得，我媽媽也記得
I remember--my mom remembers this, too--
每天早上我鑽進車裏時
I would get in the car every single day
我都會說，「你們為什麼不長高點？」
And I'd be like, "why aren't you taller?"
這就是我一直這麼矮的原因
Like, "this is why I'm so short."
我媽媽會說，「要怪就怪你爸」
She always said, "blame your dad.
「我可不矮」
I'm not that short."
她有差不多一米六八
She's 5'6".
對於亞裔女性來說這挺高的
For an asian woman, that's pretty tall.
我爸爸同樣是一米六八
And my dad's also 5'6".
帕羅奧圖中學
我想我對他在籃球上的最大影響
I think my biggest influence on him as a player,
我們聊得最多的話題
The most constant dominant conversation we had
彼得·迪潘布洛克
帕羅奧圖中學1997-2008籃球教練
是他要為其他隊員創造機會
Was him creating for others.
高中的時候，他知道他能夠在場上
In high school, he knew he could get by
好好利用他的天賦
And do well on his talent.
許多孩子，特別是他
A lot of kids, and him especially,
一心想著得分
It was all about scoring.
而我跟他聊得最多的
And my constant conversation,
也是他給我的最大難題
My constant challenge with him was,
「書豪，你有創造機會的能力
"jeremy, you're a creator.
「你真的可以當領頭人
"you could really be the man
只要你明白自己是個怎樣的球員」
If you just embraced who you are as a player."
在他高一那年
During his junior year,
林書豪在學校的維京人隊裏嶄露頭角
Jeremy emerged as the vikings' star.
隨著一場場比賽，他的技術和自信漸長
With every game, his skills and confidence grew,
但他的自負也隨之而長
But so did his ego.
有一段時間我們甚至打出30勝1負的成績
We were like 30 and 1 at one point.
那時候我們所向披靡
We were killing everybody.
我開始自我膨脹
I was starting to get a big head,
覺得自己很了不起
Thinking I was sweet and everything,
結果後來我受傷了
And then I get hurt.
高中時林書豪習慣
Jeremy had a tradition of shooting around
在比賽的前一晚練球
The night before his high school games.
但是在州半決賽的前一晚
But on the eve of the state semifinal game,
高中的體育館關門了
The high school gym was closed,
林在本地的基督教青年會打了場即興的比賽
And jeremy played in a pick-up game at his local ymca.
當晚，林書豪扭傷了腳踝
That night, jeremy fractured his ankle,
他的信念將受到考驗
And his faith would be tested.
我幾乎崩潰了
I just pretty much broke down.
我忍不住大哭
Um, I broke down crying.
在那之前，我從未經歷過嚴重的打擊
Up until then, like, I'd never gone through any serious tragedy.
那次是我當時經歷過最糟的事情
That was the worst thing that ever happened to me.
由於林書豪無法上場
With jeremy on the bench,
維京人隊獲得冠軍的希望迅速隕滅了
The vikings' hopes for a state championship quickly faded.
你知道，對於一個高中生來說
You know, from a high schooler's perspective,
那是非常大的打擊
That's like everything.
我告訴他退後一步
I told him to take a step back
用更廣闊的視角來看
And to look at it from a bigger perspective.
我記得我哥哥給我發了一封很長的信
I remember my brother sent me this really long letter.
他談到神如何給予和收回
He talks about how god gives and takes away.
神拿走了我那時特別在乎的東西
And so god took what I really cared about at that time
來說明，離開神
To show me that I can't do what I want to do,
我就不能完成我的願望
I can't accomplish what I want to accomplish without him,
這個世界上，在我的生命裏
And that nothing in this world, in my life,
沒有什麼不是按照神的旨意發生的
Will happen that's not according to his plan.
當大衛面對巨人歌利亞時
When david faced goliath,
他並不知道結果
He didn't know the outcome,
但他對神有熱忱
But he was zealous for the living god.
我知道書豪把神放在第一位
With jeremy, I know he puts the order, god first,
其次是家人，第三是籃球
Family second, basketball third.
史提芬·陳
林書豪的牧師
現在他會告訴你
And he'll tell you this now at least.
回顧過去，神主宰著這一切
Looking back, it's more of, god is in all those things.
高中時，他很謙虛
And in high school, he was humbled.
他知道不能以一己之力完成所有事情
He learned that he couldn't do everything himself.
阿門
Amen
他只能信賴神
And he could only put his faith in god.
我告訴自己
I told myself,
我只剩一年確定可以打籃球了
I have one year left of guaranteed basketball.
我要全力以赴
I said I'm gonna do everything I can,
我將力拼到底
And I'm gonna go out fighting,
我要確保我們還會回到這裏
And I'm gonna make sure that we get back here.
他的鎮定是一個高四學生少有的
He had unusual poise for a high school senior,
特別地自信
Unusual confidence.
他身上有某種東西讓我明白
There was something about him that I could see
米馳·史提芬
國內專欄作家
為什麼他在球場上是個好領袖
Why he was a great leader on the court,
因為你會不自覺被他吸引
'cause you're just driven to him.
你能感覺到他的心跳
You can feel his heartbeat.
每次他們比分很接近的時候
Every close game they had,
林書豪就會有關鍵的表現
Jeremy lin was making a big play.
每次的方式都不一樣
And it was every different way--
比賽最後關頭的三分，或者搶斷
A 3-pointer, a steal at the end of the game.
但每次都有他的參與
But every one, he was in the middle of.
他是那個挺身而出的人
He was the guy doing it.
林從右側跳投
Lin takes a jump shot right side.
中了！
Hits!
漂亮的跳投
Oh, a nice jump shot.
林的三分，有了！
Lin for 3. Buries it!
沒有什麼能夠阻止林書豪
Nothing was going to stop jeremy
把他的球隊帶回到州決賽
From getting his team back to the state championship,
很快，帕羅奧圖中學面對著自己的巨人歌利亞
And, soon enough, palo alto faced goliath.
在阿科球館裏的對陣雙方
是馬特蒂中學和帕羅奧圖中學
Announcer: Inside arco arena, it's mater dei and palo alto.
這是加州校際聯盟第二分區的州冠軍決賽
It's the cif division ii state championship
預告之後馬上開始
Just moments away from tip-off.
我想很多人都認為
I think a lot of people just assumed
能來到州冠軍決賽
That getting to the state championship game,
帕羅奧圖中學已經滿足了
Palo alto would be satisfied with.
林書豪已經滿足了
Jeremy lin would be satisfied with it.
和馬特蒂中學的比賽
And it was just much more of a formality
不過是走個形式罷了
When they played mater dei high school.
南加州的學校排名都很靠前
Southern california schools dominate the rankings.
都是強隊
They're the powers that be.
在郊區的帕羅奧圖中學，不怎麼樣
Palo alto, out in the suburbs, not so much.
人人都說，馬特蒂中學肯定贏
Everybody said mater dei was the team,
馬特蒂中學優勢很大
Mater dei is the big dog.
馬特蒂中學在全國排名11位
Mater dei, number 11 in the country.
賽前的一整個星期
The whole week leading up to the game,
我都在想，我們怎麼才能搶到籃板？
It was just like, "how we gonna get a rebound?
怎麼才能打好？
How we gonna be able to play?"
我記得在校園裏走時
I remember walking around campus,
很多記者跑來問
And there are all these reporters.
你覺得你們能贏？
And they'd be like, "oh, you think you can win?"
你們要怎麼打贏他們？
Like, "how you gonna beat 'em?"
每個人，包括我的朋友都問我
And everyone's asking me, my friends were asking me.
後來當他們問「你覺得你們能打贏他們？」
By the end, they're like, "you think you can beat 'em?"
我就說：「來看比賽就知道了。」
I was like, "man, just come to the game and watch."
馬特蒂中學不僅有
Along with mater dei's
引以為傲的歷史和強大的名氣
Decorated history and dominant reputation,
這支校隊還有8名身高1.98米以上的球員
This varsity team had 8 players over 6'6".
我聽到對手是帕羅奧圖時，還鬆了口氣
I was kindof relieved that we were playing palo alto,
格瑞·麥克奈
馬特蒂高中籃球教練
但我越看他們的錄像，越感覺到
But the more I watched them on tape, I just had a feeling.
你還別說
You know what?
這些小伙子比我想像的要厲害
These guys are better than I thought.
如果沒兩下子，是不可能打到州決賽的
You know, you don't get to the state finals by not being good.
林的球
Here's lin.
來個好球吧，他做到了
Needs something good, and he finally got it.
教練：我們一點都沒被鎮住
Diepenbrock: We were not intimidated at all
真的全力以赴打好比賽
And really came out playing our game.
林的球，這就是他們說的
Here's lin. Oh, there's that quick first step
很快的第一步
That they talked about.
帕羅奧圖打了一波9比2，到此為止
Palo alto on a 9-2 run, and that's over.
那孩子三分厲害
That kid can throw the triple.
從紙面上所有人都會說無論從體格、
Everybody on paper would say the size,
運動能力還是速度，帝王隊（對手球隊名）都更強
The athleticism, the quickness is with the monarchs,
但從鬥志來說，維京人隊更勝一籌
But it's the heart that is with the vikings,
今晚他們的鬥志得到充分的體現
And their heart has been on display so far tonight.
比賽的最後
Mcknight: At the end of the game,
他在關鍵的時刻投進了重要的球
He hit the big shots at the big moments.
林的球
Here's lin.
沒有投中距離，直接攻擊籃筐！
Without that 7-footer, he can go to the rack!
當比賽懸於一線時，他接管了比賽
When the game was on the line, yeah, he took over.
進攻時間只剩4秒了
Four seconds on the shot clock,
林不得不遠距離投籃
And lin is gonna have to launch a 25-footer.
中了！
Oh, it went in!
有意安排的嗎？我看不像
Did he call that? I think he called that.
是自然發生的
It happened.
沒有人期望他們能戰勝帝王隊
No one gave them a prayer to be on the floor
因為他們沒有帝王隊所擁有的
With the athletes and the thoroughbreds
精心培養的運動人才
That the monarchs have.
到達最高點，這是最棒的感覺
It's the best feeling to go out on top.
這就是美夢成真
I mean, it is a dream come true.
這就是為什麼我喜歡高中籃球
It's why we love high school basketball
因為這樣的笑臉
Because of faces like that.
教練：當我縱觀這一切
Diepenbrock: When I really looked at everything,
一個籃球運動員
Everything a basketball player
能夠為他自己
Could do for himself individually
為球隊做的一切
And for a team,
林書豪都是這裏最好的球員
Jeremy lin was the best player here,
可是大學並沒有爭著要他
But yet colleges weren't clamoring for him.
他不符合固有的模式
He just didn't fit the mold.
高中畢業時
After my senior year,
我非常想在大學打籃球
I was just dying to play in college,
而且覺得自己有這個實力
And I felt like I deserved it.
15.4分
6.2助攻
4.2搶斷
北加州第二分區
年度最佳球員
全加州第一陣容球員
我記得那個過程很長
I remember it was just a very long process,
感覺很沮喪，因為我問了一間又一間的
Very frustrating,because I was going
太平洋十校聯盟的院校
From pac 10 school to pac 10 school.
太平洋十校聯盟：是一個美國西部的大學體育聯盟，
成員包括斯坦福大學等名校，現已改名為太平洋十二校聯盟
我甚至得不到
I couldn't even get
第三分區的學校青睞
Some division iii schools to look at me.
而我特別想去斯坦福大學
And I was dying to go to stanford.
我常常去他們學校打球
Um, I would go there and play with them all the time.
我會問他們的教練
I would always ask their coach, you know,
我怎樣才能到你隊裏打球？
"what can I do to play for you?"
是，我常說如果我是黑人
Yeah, I've always said, if I was black,
我會得到第一分區學校的獎學金
I would have gotten a d-1 scholarship,
但那只是我的個人意見
But that's my personal opinion.
教練：他是個亞裔孩子
Diepenbrock: Well, he's an asian kid.
沒有兩米身高的亞裔孩子
He's an asian kid, and he's not 7-foot tall.
你很少見到亞裔的控衛
And you don't see a lot of asian point guards
能進入第一分區的籃球隊
Making it in division I basketball.
想法很簡單，但那就是他們的想法
Such a simple kind of thought, but that was the thinking.
我會說，他和我有共鳴
I say...I say he's relatable.
范振書亞
林書豪的朋友
他是我見過最腳踏實地的人之一
He's one of the most down-to-earth guys I know.
我們總是開玩笑
We're always joking around.
總是互相搞惡作劇
We're always, you know, pranking on each other.
你看到那些藍色的點綴嗎？
Um, did you see the blue accented stuff?
我看到啊，你喜歡那種藍色？
I did see it. You like that blue?
是，我很喜歡那種藍色
Yeah. I really like that blue,
因為我走進來時
'cause when I walk in,
我不要只有黑和白
I don't want it to be like black, white, black.
我要大家都驚嘆
I want people to be like, "dang."
哇，這個
Oh, shoot, son.
不同的牆壁需要不同的點綴
Different walls need different accents.
這些是清倉甩賣的
These are clearance.
哇，看這個
Yeah, dang, look at that.
看，才10美元
Look at this. 10 bucks.
人們跟他一起的時候
I think when people hang out with him,
他們會發現
They just realize he's just...
他就是個普通人
You know, he's human.
聽著不錯，好，再見
Sounds good. All right, see you later, bro.
雖然被評為年度最佳球員
Despite being named player of the year
還獲得了加州冠軍
And winning a state championship,
林書豪得到的唯一一份
Jeremy's only offer
能夠打籃球的大學錄取通知
To play basketball on the collegiate level
是一所「小」學校
Was from a small university
哈佛
Called harvard.
第一天上課
My first day at class,
我被徹底嚇著了
I was just super-intimidated.
我去參加數學分班測驗
I went and took my math placement test,
他們說，如果你不會做
And they were like, "if you don't know how to do this,
可以交卷走人
Feel free to turn it in and leave."
我看著試卷，心想
I looked at it and I was, like,
天吶，我啥也看不懂
"dude, I don't know what's going on here."
於是我交了卷
So I turned it in, and I was,
我大概是第二個交卷的
Like, maybe the second person who turned it in.
我心想，天，我在哈佛的
I was like, "man, I just, like,
第一場測驗就掛了
Failed my first test at harvard."
第二天，我們進行中文分班測驗
The next day, we had the chinese placement test,
然後他們說
And they gave us the test, and they're like,
如果你讀不懂，可以交卷
"if you can't read it, just turn it in."
我讀不懂啊，就又交卷了
I couldn't read it, so I turned it in again,
那是連續兩次測驗掛掉
And that was back-to-back failed tests
我甚至一個答案都寫不出
Without even filling in an answer.
我在電話裏跟我媽媽說
I called my mom, I was like, "man,
以後估計很難熬了，要做好心理準備
This is gonna be pretty tough, so just get ready."
很大程度上，林書豪去哈佛
In a lot of ways, jeremy lin going to harvard
是符合邏輯的
Was a very logical thing.
哈佛有23名
There were 23 asian-americans at harvard
姓林的亞裔學生
Whose last name was lin.
所以林進入哈佛
And so for jeremy lin to show up at harvard,
作為亞裔的孩子
Being this asian-american kid,
數學成績好
Who had a perfect math sat ii score was,
你也知道，並不少見
You know, nothing rare.
但是他打籃球很厲害的這個事實（卻很特別）
But the fact that he was amazing at this game,
問題是他如何融入哈佛？
The question was then how did he fit in at harvard?
湯米·艾默科
There is tommy amaker,
1987年畢業於杜克大學（籃球名校）
1987 graduate of duke, of course,
這是在哈佛的第一年
First year at harvard,
已經有11年的主教練經驗
11th year overall as a head coach,
180場勝利
180 career wins.
隨著前密歇根大學的教練湯米·艾默科的到來
With the hiring of former michigan coach tommy amaker,
哈佛決心走進
Harvard was committed to a new era
籃球上的新時代
In their basketball program.
艾默科在杜克大學是明星球員
Amaker was a star player at duke university,
後來當了九年的助教
Then spent nine years as an assistant coach
輔佐傳奇教練邁克·沙捨夫斯基（老K教練）
To the legendary mike krzyzewski.
哈佛的籃球版圖
The basketball landscape at harvard
正準備改頭換面
Was about to be transformed,
而林書豪是排頭兵
And jeremy was leading the charge.
我知道我們有些特別的因素
We knew we had something pretty interesting,
特別是林書豪
Especially with jeremy,
因為首先他訓練特別刻苦
Because of how hard he worked, first of all,
而且籃球對他而言非常重要
And how important basketball was to him.
還有就是他的天賦
And then his talent.
我認為他被大大地低估了
I think he was very much underrated,
我認為他想按照
And I think he wanted to play in the style
我們推行的
And the system, you know,
風格和系統打球
That we weregonna implement,
也就是高能量的風格
Which is gonna be high octane.
他的球風很強硬
And he's a hard-charging,
侵略性強，無所畏懼
Aggressive, fearless player.
林書豪斷球
A steal by jeremy lin.
輕鬆扣籃
He's gonna go in for the easy jam.
抬頭看
Looking up ahead,
林撕裂了防守並成功上籃！
Lin splits defenders and lays it in!
我做教練15年
In my 15 years of coaching,
在杜克大學打了4年球
My four years at duke,
我從來沒見過任何人
I've never seen anybody
像林書豪那麼努力
Work as diligent and as hard as jeremy.
他每天都來，認真訓練
He came in every day and put the work in.
我們每天看錄像
We watched film every day.
肯尼·佈雷肯尼
哈佛大學2007-2011男籃助教
我們訓練前後也在練習
We did work before and after practice.
他非常勤奮
He busted his tail,
我們要求他做的，他都做到了
And he did all the things that we asked him to do.
弧頂出手，大三分，林書豪！
Top of the circle, deep 3, jeremy lin!
似乎比賽場面越大，他打得越好
It seems the bigger the game, the better he played.
這是一場大東部的籃球賽
It's big east basketball,
排名第13的康涅狄格大學哈士奇隊
對陣哈佛大學的猩紅隊
As the 13th ranked uconn huskies host the crimson of harvard.
今天要注意的是林書豪
Now, keep an eye on jeremy lin today.
這樣的球員
This is the type of player
能夠只手幫助猩紅隊
That can single-handedly help the crimson
起死回生
Pull off a miraculous upset.
艾默科：他是場上最棒的球員
Amaker: He was the best player on the floor.
那說明了很多事情
You know, that's saying a lot
當你面對的是
When you're speaking of a team
像康涅狄格大學這樣的球隊時
that was the caliber of connecticut.
哇！
Wow!
多漂亮的籃底動作
What a move on the runner off the glass.
我想那時候大家都認為
I think that's when everybody was like,
他不只是一個好的大學球員這麼簡單
"all right, he's more than just, like, a good college player.
奧利佛·麥克納裏
後衛，哈佛大學籃球隊2008-2012
他讓一支很厲害的球隊顏面盡失
Like, he just made a very good team look bad."
凱西球被打出去，戴森搶斷
Casey had it knocked away,and a steal by dyson.
林跟到籃下
Takes lin to the basket,
林在籃邊給他一個蓋帽！
And lin blocks him at the rim!
漂亮的蓋帽
What a block.
艾默科：他拿了30分
Amaker: Scoring 30 points there,
在各方面都有貢獻
Being a force to deal with in every way.
回到林手上，來到禁區，假動作，切到籃下
Back to lin top of the key, pump fake, drives
雙手扣進！
And throws it down with both hands!
林書豪的漂亮扣籃！
Oh, what a dunk by jeremy lin!
他讓我們一直相信
He kept us believing all the way through
我們有機會
That we have a chance.
這小子在各個方面都領導者這支球隊
This guy's leading this team in every category, not just one.
丹·達根
體育作者，波士頓先驅報
他不只是個得分手
I mean, it wasn't like he was just a scorer.
他還是最好的防守隊員
He was the best defensive player,
搶籃板最好，傳球最好
He was the best rebounder, the best passer.
他基本上什麼都最好
You know, he pretty much could do it all.
在那些時刻
It was just kind of like those moments
關鍵的時刻或者決定勝負的時刻
Where it was crunch time and winning time,
誰會站出來？
You know, who's gonna step up?
回到另一邊，給到葛迪
Back the other way, comes to gurdy,
進入前場
Into the frontcourt.
切入到右側
Drives down the right lane line,
右手上籃！中了！
Goes up with the right hand! Lays it in!
只剩三秒！哈佛回到另一邊！
Three seconds left! Harvard back the other way!
落後一分，林書豪！
Down by a point, jeremy lin!
中場被撞倒！
Bumped at midcourt!
他被犯規，但還是投進了！
He's fouled, but got it to go!
哈佛贏了！哈佛贏了！
Harvard wins it! Harvard wins it!
難以置信！
Unbelievable!
林書豪投進了難以置信的一球
Jeremy lin on an unbelievable shot,
哈佛贏了！
And harvard has won
以最不可思議的方式！
In the most improbable fashion!
不敢相信！
I don't believe it!
我小時候
When I was growing up,
參加AAU的比賽
I was playing in the aau tournaments.
我們比賽的時候
We would play in games,
有時候，人們會說
And a couple of times, people would be like,
「喲，滾回到中國去」
"yo, take your ass back to china,"
或者說：「你就是個中國貨」之類的
Or like, "you're a chinese import," or whatever.
上了大學以後，這些攻擊更離譜了
When I got to college, it just, like, got crazy.
比如說：「中國佬！」
It was just like, "you chink!"
什麼「你能張開眼睛嗎？」
You know, "can you even open your eyes?
你看得見分數牌嗎？
Can you see the scoreboard?"
這種亂七八糟的東西
You know, just like crazy stuff.
我心想：這都什麼跟什麼啊？
And I'd just be like, "dude, like, what is going on?"
身處目光的焦點中
Being in the spotlight
為林書豪帶來不可避免的副產物
Brought jeremy an inevitable byproduct:
關注，有正面的，也有負面的
Attention, both positive and negative.
人們在看籃球運動員時
I mean, people look at basketball players in terms of...
如果用種族的角度去看
Of race a lot of times.
在美國，籃球往往被視為
Basketball is not considered
不是給亞裔玩的運動
An asian sport here in america.
我們打客場時
We'd be playing on the road,
在常春藤的某個體育館裏
Specific gyms in the ivy league,
他們會向他喊一些種族歧視的髒話
And they would yell racial slurs to him.
在常春藤聯盟，看到種族歧視的辱罵
It was shocking to me to see racial taunts
讓我很驚訝
In the ivy league,
到了這個級別
Because you think that at that level,
當然你會認為
Certainly in the supposed, you know,
學術氛圍應該很濃厚
Very academically progressively oriented
這些校園裏會有很多亞裔的學生
Group of schools full of asian students on their campuses
種族歧視的侮辱應該是不可想像的
That that would be something that was unthinkable,
但事實並非如此
But it wasn't.
我告訴他，這是一種重視的表現
I just told him, it's a sign of respect.
是，他們很無知
Yeah, they're ignorant,
但說到底
But at the end of the day,
是他們想要進入你的腦子
They're trying to get in your head.
你在想著他們說的東西
You're thinking about what they saying
而沒有想著比賽
And not thinking about the game.
好像是在訓練中
I think we were just working out,
我對他說
And kind of was like, you know
書豪，能跟你說句話嗎？
"j, can I speak to you for a moment?"
他讓我坐下
He sat me down,
4.4 助攻/場
4.4 籃板/場
16.4 分/場
總共 1,483 分
坐在體育館外的樓梯上
Like, right outside the gym on the stairs,
他說
And he was like...
我不知道有沒有人告訴過你
"I don't know if anybody's ever told you this,
但我覺得你可以去打NBA
But I think you can be an nba player."
他看著我的表情
And he kind of looked at me like, you know,
就像看到聖誕老人
He just saw santa claus or something.
我說，你瘋了吧
You know, I was just like, "you're crazy," you know.
我說，兄弟，你肯定瘋了
I was like, "dude, you are crazy."
我媽媽會說
My mom, you know, would be like,
你可以去打NBA
"you can make it to the nba."
呃，好吧……媽
"all right. Um, okay, mom."
這可能嗎？
Is this possible?
我想也許他真的
I thought maybe he really...
有這個可能
Really have a chance.
當這個問題被提起
When the question was broached,
林書豪是不是有能力進入NBA
Is jeremy lin good enough to make the nba,
我想正是從那時開始他對這件事情產生興趣
That's when I think a lot of the interest started surging.
能告訴我這張毯子的來歷嗎？
Can you tell me the history of this blanket?
這張毯子來頭可大了
Oh, this blanket is legendary.
是嗎？
Yeah?
上面全是《獅子王》的角色
It's all about lion king.
這裏有娜娜
We have nala right here,
還有小辛巴，丁滿和彭彭
Baby simba, timon and pumbaa.
這是我一直以來最喜歡的毯子
This is one of my favorite blankets of all time.
芝麻街那條毯子呢？
What about the sesame street blanket?
不，我第二喜歡的是那條加菲貓的
No. My second favorite is the garfield,
然後才到芝麻街那條
And then sesame street.
天……好吧，球迷們
oh, man. All right, fans.
晚上好，歡迎來到2010年度選秀
Good evening, and welcome to the 2010 draft
來到紐約的麥迪遜花園
At madison square garden in new york city.
第一輪，我們也沒抱什麼期望
The first round, we weren't expecting really much of anything.
今晚意味著
Tonight marks the realization of a dream
世界上最好的年輕球員夢想成真
For the best young players in the world.
我們都很緊張
We were just all real nervous,
因為他需要克服很多障礙
Just 'cause there were so many odds to overcome for him.
狀元簽，華盛頓巫師隊(奇才隊)
And with the first pick, the washington wizards
選擇來自肯塔基大學的約翰·沃爾
Select john wall from the university of kentucky.
我確實滿懷著希望，但是說實在話
I was hopeful,but to be completely honest
心裏真正想的是：拭目以待到底會發生什麼吧
I was like, "let's just wait and see what happens."
我一直留意著種族問題
The thing that I'm always interested in is race
聯盟裏種族歧視這種風氣一直存在
And the way discrimination,you know, rears its ugly head.
我很好奇是否有球隊會嘗試冒險
I was really interested in seeing if a team would take the plunge
去選一個美籍亞裔球員
And take this asian-american player.
有意思的是
You know, it was funny.
我最有機會選上的球隊
Like, the team that I had the highest chance
是尼克斯
To get drafted b was the knicks,
因為我在試訓裏打得特別好
cause I crushed that workout.
2010 NBA選秀大會第39順位是
With the 39th pick in the 2010 nba draft...
我想「如果在這裏我沒有被選中」
I was like,"if I don'get drafted here
我很有可能就不會被任何球隊選了
I probably won't get drafted."
紐約尼克斯隊的選擇是
The new york knicks select...
我想「天啊，如果我被選中了我該做些什麼？」
I'm thinking like,"oh, if I get drafted，what's gonna happen?
我應該要圍著會場跑一圈，擁抱每個人嗎？
I'm just gonna run around, like，hugging everyone
明天我就要飛去紐約了
I'm gonna fly to new york tomorrow
蘭德裏·菲爾茲，來自斯坦福大學
Landry fields，from stanford university.
選秀結束後十分鐘
10 minutesafter the draft ended,
達拉斯小牛隊的經理唐尼.尼爾森
Donny nelson,the general manager
親自打電話給林書豪
Of the dallas mavericks,personally called jeremy
讓他為小牛隊夏季聯賽效力
And asked him to playon his summer league team.
我想大概每個落選的人
I think everyone who goes undrafted,you know,
都會有一種想要證明自己的心情，因為他們覺得自己有實力
Feels like they have to prove themselves,because they do.
因此，這對我而言確實是一個好機會
And so, you know,this is a chance
你在夏季聯賽的賽場
Where you get to play against people
每晚跟選秀大會上落選的球員們一起打球
Who are drafted every single night
你要在實戰中與他們競爭
And you get to compete with them in practice
而這恰好就是最好的機會
And this is the best opportunity to, you know
證明給所有的球隊看
Prove to all the other teams
你是值得被選中的
That you deserved to be drafted
你本來應該得到一份合同
And you deserved to have that contract
林書豪，巧妙的進攻
Lin, surprise attack
這將是一場很有看頭的比賽
Oh, this is gonna be interesting
桑德斯在防守，林成功保住這一球！
Sanders there，lin protected it home!
哇！漂亮的進球
Wow! Nice play.
我希望林書豪能成功
I hoped that jeremy would make it
因為我對他的實力有信心
Because I had confidence in his ability,
但是我疑慮的是
But I was skeptical
是否有一處可以讓他真正一展身手的地方
In terms of him getting a real shot anywhere.
林書豪！
Jeremy lin!
接著在夏季聯賽
And then I watched him play
我看到了他與沃爾的對決
In the summer league against john wall
我們將看到非常精彩的對位
I think we got a primetime match-up
約翰·沃爾，聯盟選秀的狀元
John wall, the number one overall selection
沃爾進攻！反手上籃！
Wall, creative!On the reverse.
速度夠快吧？
How fast was that?
在比賽前一天我告訴林書豪
I talked to him the day before
他將跟約翰·沃爾對位
He was gonna play against john wall
這是你關鍵的一次表現機會
And I told him,"it's your one shot
跟沃爾對位你完全沒有問題
There's no doubt that you can play against the guy."
林書豪，單手上籃！
Lin.Lin gettin' up there!
林將成為聯盟裏的新寵
He's gonna be an nba crowd favorite
在進攻端再次得手
Gotta work on the end.
林在右路繞過防守，在他習慣的右路上籃
Lin went right around him on his strong side
林書豪具有
The fact that he could do that
與新秀狀元對位的能力，這個事實令人激動
Against the number-one player in the nba draft was tremendous
評估，建設性的意見
Assessing,constructive criticism
好球！
No way. Man!
如果你激發出他的能力，你會看到意想不到的事情
If you explode on him,you'll have something.
你會看到他身上蘊藏著無限的可能
You're gonna get your opportunity
他撕開防守，轉身投籃
As he splits,spins...
太可惜了！裁判為什麼要吹哨子？！
Oh, no, ref!Don't you do that!
觀眾們都站起來了！
They're on their feet!
天呀，這恐怕是要引起一場混戰啊
Oh, my god.This is about to be a melee here
拉開他們（解說員開玩笑）
Hold 'em back,hold 'em back!
快看，觀眾們已經陷入瘋狂了
Oh, look it, the crowd is going crazy!
他改變了一些人的狹隘眼光
He's opened some eyes
如果林不再留在小牛為夏季聯賽效力
And if lin doesn't stick with the mavs
會有球隊看著他的表現，心想
There are teams out there that are looking at him saying,
天吶，他完全推翻了我們的觀念
"boy, he beats their system very nicely."
不管他今年是否留在夏季聯賽
Whether he's in the league this year or not
都會有幾支球隊想要他的
He'll have some options
是的，會有幾支球隊想要他的
Oh, he will have some options.
我只是一心想要打球
I'm just trying to play
只要有球隊有興趣與我談
And if someone's interested, you know,
我非常樂意去爭取機會
I'd love to talk about an opportunity.
我的兒子跟林書豪都是組織後衛
Joe lacob: My son and he both were point guards
他們在AAU分屬不同的球隊
And they were on different aau teams
喬·拉可布
金州勇士隊老闆
記得在當地的體育館
And so I remember watching them play
我看過他們的AAU比賽
These aau games in these local gyms.
當時我跟我的合夥人正好買下了勇士隊
But I just happened to buy the team at that time with my partners.
我最早跟總經理說的其中一件事就是
One of the first things I told our gm was,
「我知道那個球員，我的兒子也知道他」
"look, I know this kid.My son knows this kid.」
他非常有天賦，我們應該給他一個機會「
He's really talented.We ought to give him a shot."
我想他們都覺得我有點瘋了
I think they thought we were a little crazy,
但是我們還是那麼做了，當你是老闆
But we did, and, you know,when you're the owner,
你就有權利做些瘋狂的事
You get to do things like that
勇士隊球員的平均智商以及籃球智商
The warriors' iq and basketball iq
都上升了一些
Just went up a few points
因為他們簽了哈佛畢業的後衛林書豪
They signed harvard guard jeremy lin
我打給林書豪告訴他我們將簽下他
I called jeremy to tell him.
羅傑·蒙哥馬利
林書豪的經紀人
他甚至不相信這是真的
He didn't believe me.
他說「別開玩笑了，你是認真的嗎？」
He was like,"stop playing, man.Are you serious?"
我說「小伙子，這是真的」
I said,"man, it's for real
「明天就來場地練習」
"go down to the practice facility tomorrow
「然後簽下合同，很好吧」
And sign the contract.It's good."
於是他說「老兄，我待會給你回電！」
And he was like,"man! I'll call you back."
你知道我幾乎不敢相信「天啊」
I was like, "aah!"you know
我叫醒我弟弟
I picked my little brother up,
跟他說：金州勇士隊簽我了
I'm like, "I'm signing with golden state!"
我又跑到另一個房間
And I ran into the next room,
叫醒我哥哥
I picked my other brother up.
「勇士隊要跟我簽約了！」
"I'm signing with golden state!"
我很難描述是怎樣一種心情
I can't even really describe it
因為我們兄弟從小就為NBA著迷
cause we, like, grew up,like, fantasizing about the nba
我們從小到大都支持著勇士隊
And, like, the fact that we grew up rooting for the warriors
這一切使書豪進入勇士隊顯得更不可思議
Made it even that much crazier
作為當代的第一位美籍亞裔NBA球員
Lin has a chance to make history
林書豪很有機會創造歷史
As the first asian-americannba player in the modern era
當他被勇士選中
When he got picked up by warriors
那個時刻我們想
That moment,we think
「這就是我希望他做的事情」
"this is what I want him to do."
我的夢想就是在NBA打球
My dream was to play in the nba,
現在我即將在勇士隊完成我的夢想
And now I get to do it for the warriors
我是看著這支球隊的比賽長大的
The team that I grew up watching
所以加入勇士隊的意義比夢想成真還要深遠
It's more than a dream come true
我們都知道觀眾為什麼歡呼，林書豪上場了
We know what that's about
林書豪，曾是帕羅奧多高中的學生
Jeremy lin.Palo alto high school's own
畢業於哈佛的勇士新秀
Warrior rookie out of harvard
當時我上場的時候球館歡呼聲很大
It got pretty loud
觀眾們站起來為我鼓掌
And people were standing up and clapping
我環顧四周
And I just remember looking around
從小是勇士隊的球迷
Grew up a warrior fan
長大後被他家鄉的球隊簽下
Signed by his hometown team
這是一個了不起的故事
It's a great story
確實如此
It really is.
我終於來到勇士隊，我終於成為勇士隊的一員
It was so emotional for me to finally get there
這真的讓我感慨良多
For me to finally be there
一年前我真的不敢想像我會出現在那裏
And I couldn't envision myself there even a year ago.
當我看著他防守科比，我的感覺真的是（難以言喻）「哇~」
When I saw him guarding kobe,I was like, "wow."
我們從小就看科比比賽
We've been watching this guy ever since we were little
他現在……居然可以和科比同時在場上
He's actually...He's there.
沒進，大衛李拿下籃板球
Missing,lee with the rebound.
我喜歡看林控球，不要犯規阻礙他
I love what lin did.Didn't foul him
啊~！
Ohh!
準備給灰熊還一記顏色
Ready to returnfor the grizzlies.Williams
林有一個空檔
Lin's got an open look
結果莫名其妙把球傳給了巴蒂爾
And then threw it to battier inexplicably
歡迎來到NBA
Welcome to the nba
我討厭所有人都盯著我看
I hate when everyone's looking at me
我討厭聚光燈
I hate the spotlight
我如何保持心態做我自己
How am I gonna be myself
每當我碰到球
When every time I touch the ball,
每個人都期待著我有瘋狂的表現
Everyone's expecting me to do
期待我帶來不可思議的比賽
Some crazy, miraculous play?
他得分了！
He scores!
觀眾們可以從我的表情看出一些端倪
People could see it on my face
譬如我在場上打球
Like, I was out there playing
但是我並沒有打出自己風格
But I wasn't playing my brand of basketball
我覺得焦慮不安
I was scared, nervous
心裏有很多的疑惑
And just, like,a lot of questions
巨大的壓力
And a lot of stress
感覺周圍有很多的不確定因素擾亂在心間
And a lot of uncertainty floating around
他缺少那麼點運氣
The ingredient that's missing
拉裏·萊利
金州勇士隊
2009-2012年總經理
球隊裏已經有兩個排在他前面的後衛了
Is the fact there was a player named monta ellis
蒙塔埃利斯和庫裏
And steph curry ahead of him
在NBA水準的比賽裏，教練們無疑都想贏球
You know, coaches need to win,at the nba level
當時我們隊的教練基思·斯瑪特
And so keith smart, who was our coach at the time,
確實沒怎麼讓他上場
Really didn't play him a lot
事情就是這樣
And this is how these things happen
一開始我告訴自己
At first, I was like,
「他知道我有實力，他知道我可以上場比賽」
"he knows I can play,he knows I can play."
可是事實是我基本上沒有機會上場
And then I wasn't playing at all,
然後我看到體育新聞裏寫
And then I was, like,reading all these articles like,
「看吧，把他簽進來只是為了多賣幾件球衣」
"oh, he's just here to sell jerseys
「然後增加球隊的收入」
And increase revenue."
我想：也許這就是事實
I was like,maybe that's all it is
也許這就是我在這兒起的作用
Maybe that's all I'm good for, you know
說實話我們得對自己坦誠一些
I think we have to be honest with ourselves
簽林書豪進來肯定是考慮到了市場因素
There was definitely a marketing element to it
我的意思是說他是我們自己家鄉人
I mean,he's a hometown guy
這裏有很大比重的亞裔人口
The area has a significant asian-american population
一切都證明了確實是那樣的
And the way it played out
灣區的球迷為他瘋狂
You know, people went bonkers for that
在許多美國人眼裏亞洲人是十分遙遠和陌生的
A lot of what america perceives as asian is very foreign
姚明是一個典型的例子
Yao ming was kind of a quintessential example of that
他來自中國，他來自東方
He's from china, he's from the east
到達我們的海岸
And he's coming to our shores
但是林書豪卻不同 ，他是本土產的
Whereas,jeremy is like homegrown
他是在美國本土郊外長大的亞裔小孩
He's a homegrown asian-american kid from the suburbs
跟美國其他小孩一樣懷著籃球夢長大
He grew up with hoop dreams just like the rest of us
看著像林書豪這樣的孩子在球場上
Seeing a kid like jeremy on the court
穿著勇士隊的隊服
In a warriors uniform,
這給我們很大的衝擊
You know,that's a huge impact
你知道，他很開心能為自己家鄉的球隊效力
You know, he was happy to be playing for his hometown team
但是，我們並不滿足於只是進入NBA
But we weren't satisfied with just being in the nba
球迷想看到林書豪衝到籃下
Fans want jeremy lin to go all the way to the rim
但是球卻被搶走了
And he has it taken away
勇士的管理層
The warriors' management
把林書豪下放到發展聯盟
Sent jeremy down to the d-league
這是NBA的小型聯盟育才體系
The nba's versionof a minor league farm system
他面對著殘酷的現實
He was faced with a harsh reality.
發展聯盟是一道難關
The d-league is one of the toughest things
對於籃球生涯而言
When it comes to a basketball career.
發展聯盟，你懂的，它是個展示的舞台
The d- league, you know, it's a showcase
人們不在乎你贏了多少場
People don't care how many wins you have.
他們只在乎你的數據
All they care about is your stats.
一切都只與你自己有關，雖然你有隊友
It's all about you, and you have teammates,
但他們其實並不和你站在同一戰線上
But they're not really on your team.
如果可以的話，他們會搶了你的飯碗
You know, they'll take your job if they can.
你能搶斷？
You cut off?
你是控衛嗎？
You the point guard?
是的
Yeah.
你把球傳給我
You pass it to me...
好的
Okay.
然後你就在那兒等著
And then just wait out there.
當他去發展聯盟的時候，我對他說的話很簡單
What I told him when he went to the d-league was simple.
把它拿下
Go kill it.
去把發展聯盟搞定，然後等著別人給我們打電話
Go and crush the d-league, and let's get called up.
因為這是一場戰役
Because it's a battle, you know.
這就是一場意志上的戰役
It's a battle right here.
我在想，"天啊，如果我弄砸了"
I was like, "man, like, if I play bad,
我可能就這樣了
This may be it."
林書豪奮力帶球
Jeremy lin drives against squeaky,
試圖靠近籃架，但把球丟了
to get to the rack, throws it away!
我睡不著覺，因為我壓力太大了
I couldn't really sleep, 'cause I was so stressed.
我給我哥哥打電話
I called my brother.
我說，「我現在很糾結」
I was like, "I'm trippin' right now,
我都不知道這是在幹嘛
Like, I don't know what's going on."
我想，對他來說，就像是這段旅程
I think, for him, it was just like the journey
讓他筋疲力盡了一樣
Was kind of wearing on him.
因為這條路上的每一步
'cause, like, at every step of the way,
你都要克服所有這些障礙
You have to, like, overcome all these odds,
我認為，到了某個時間點上
And, like, I think at a certain point,
這些障礙讓他感覺不可逾越
It felt insurmountable for him.
所以他那個時候狀態不是很好
So he was not in a good place.
林需要穩定下來
Lin needs to settle down.
沒錯，他快沒有力氣了
Yeah, he's running out of gas.
林書豪極力地想要證明
Jeremy desperately wanted to prove
他屬於NBA，但在他的新秀賽季
That he belonged, but in his rookie year,
他被3次下放到了發展聯盟
He was sent to the d-league three times.
我想他被這樣送來送去
I think getting sent back and forth
這種經常性來回搖擺的效應
And the constant yo-yo effect
源於被勇士隊調回來
Of being taken up by the warriors,
又下放回去
Sent back down,
其積累性的結果就是給他沉重的負擔
The cumulative effect of it weighed heavily on him.
你知道，我一直有那種渴望
You know, I've always had that desire,
我一直有那種渴望在我心中
And I've always had that within me
證明我能在NBA打球
Where I want to prove that I could play in the nba.
但是，你知道，我現在在這裏是有原因的
But, you know, I'm here right now for a reason,
並且，你知道，神以不同的方式在起作用
And, you know, god works in very different ways.
保持住！保持住！來這兒！
Stay up! Stay up! Come here!
我覺得隨著每場比賽
You know,I thought with each game,
他的自信心都在增強，並且你能看得到
His confidence grew,and you could see it
這幾乎是伴隨著每次場上的持球
Almost with each possession up the floor.
在他打了20場比賽的那段時間之後
And after his 20-game stint,
我覺得他走出了那段發展聯盟經歷的陰影
I think he came out of that d-league experience
埃裏克·穆蘇曼
大角羊隊主教練（發展聯盟）
開始相信他能在NBA中闖出名堂
Really believing that he could have an impact in the nba.
那時候很困難，因為我們知道他能打球
It was tough, because we knew he could play.
讓人很沮喪的是，很多人
It was just frustrating because so many people
就只想著拋棄他，放棄他
Were so ready to just bury him and give up on him.
這對我來說很難
It's hard for me,
因為我真的很熱愛籃球
Because I really love basketball.
就像是，我愛我的夢想
Like, I love my dream.
我的夢想就是打NBA
My dream is to play in the nba,
我太想實現這個夢想了，以致於我都無法想像
And I wanted it so bad that I couldn't imagine
在最後快要實現這個夢想的時候，卻又馬上失去了它
Finally getting it, and then losing it right away.
這裏有人認為詹姆斯現在沒有科比強嗎？
Does anyone in here think lebron is not as good as kobe right now?
我認為詹姆斯當然沒比（科比）強
I think lebron is definitely not better,
他只是更壯實
Just bigger.
好吧，這有點難講
Well, it's kind of hard to say.
你比我們知道得更清楚，所以……
You'd know better than us, so...
不，我也不清楚
No, I don't know.
我只是坐得比你們近一些而已
I just had closer seats.
大一些的孩子們？
Older kids?
2011林書豪籃球訓練營
嘿，你們來這裏
Hey, you guys are in here. In here.
教練：不錯，完美
Coach: Nice, perfect.
然後左邊，左邊，或者右邊，右邊。很棒
And then left, left,or a right, right. Perfect.
好，我喜歡這個
Yeah, I like that.
這裏有一個很好的組
This is a good group right here!
嘿，不要動，不要動，不要動，不要動
Hey! Don't move, don't move,don't move, don't move!
就呆在那兒
Stay out there.
所有這些亞裔孩子，好像，都被我嚇壞了
All these asian kidsare, like, intimidated by me.
我跟他們講話，他們就像，」呃……「
like talk to them, they're like, "uh..."
我就說，」小兄弟，我可不是，科學怪人哦「
I'm like, "dude, I'm not, like, frankenstein."
如果對手很高的話，你就會被堵住
If they're really tall,you're gonna get stuck,
你就會被判走步
And then you'll get called for a travel.
來這裏
Right here.
裏奇有些話要說
Ricky has something to say.
謝謝你
Thank you.
沒事，謝謝你們能來
No problem.Thanks for coming.
我記得我在發展聯盟的時候，我有寫日記
I remember in the d-league, I kept a little diary.
我知道這對你們來說，有點女孩子氣
I know that's a little girlie to some of you guys,
但我喜歡寫下我的想法
But I like to write down some of my thoughts
偶爾寫一下
Every once in a while
好讓我可以回顧和想起來
So I can look back and remember.
我記得在12月29號
And I remember on December 29th,
我寫到，其實我多麼希望
I wrote about how I actually wish
我從來沒有和勇士隊簽約
I had never signed with the warriors.
我希望我能放棄籃球，因為我當時無法從中得到樂趣
I wish I could quit basketball, because I wasn't having fun.
讓我熬過那段日子的是--
And what got me through those times--
顯然，我現在沒有那種感受了
Obviously, I don't feel that way now.
但當時讓我熬過那段日子的也是
But what got me through that time
今天所有領導者會在這裏最重要的原因
Was the number one reason why all the leaders are here today.
那就是我們想讓你們知道
And that's because we want to let you guys know
神愛我，並且他有一個完美的計劃給我
That god loves me and that he has a perfect plan for me,
他的計劃會帶你
And that his plan will take you
經歷很多起起落落
Through a lot of ups and downs,
但如果我一直堅信神
But if I stay faithful to him,
最後，我知道神一定會起作用的
In the end,I know that he's gonna work
所有事情都是為了我好
Everything for my good.
現在當我打籃球的時候
Now when I play basketball,
我不再為了任何人或事去打球
I don't play for anybody else anymore.
我只為神打球
I only play for god.
這就是神給我的目的
And that's the type of purpose that he gave me,
他一旦賦予我目的性
And once he gave me that purpose,
那就是我獲得內心安寧的時候
Then that's when I had my peace.
一旦我獲得安寧，我就獲得了喜悅
And once I got my peace, that's when I got my joy.
有時候換一種風景
Sometimes a change of scenery
可以轉變對人生的看法
Can shift a perspective on life.
對我來說知道我的根是很重要的
My roots is important for me to know,
因為那就代表著我是誰
Because it's who I am.
這是我身份的很大一部分
It's a huge part of my identity.
我瞭解我的父母來自哪裏
I understand where my parents came from,
他們是如何在那種文化裏成長的
How they grew up in the culture.
哦！你把玩偶弄掉了
Oh! Oh! You dropped it!
你把它弄掉了
You dropped it!
這就是我每年回來的原因
So that's why I come back every summer
就是為了好好感受一下
Just to get a good feel for that.
我為我的身份感到驕傲
I'm very proud to be, you know, who I am.
回到農場
Back on the farm.
我現在還是退後一點吧
Oh, I'm gonna back up a little bit now.
（台語）
來看看我父親成長的地方
Seeing where my dad grew up,
所以40年間可以發生巨大變化
So 40 years makes a huge difference,
你知道，從他在這裏成長
You know, from him growing up here
到我們在美國成長
To how we grew up in the U.S.
這真的是一個很卑微的起步
It's definitely humble beginnings.
嘿，兄弟，你看到那蝦了嗎？
Hey, man, you see this shrimp?
哦，嘿，小心點
Oh, hey, hey. Watch yourself.
我的祖父母是在中國出生、長大的
My grandparents are born and raised in china.
我的父母在台灣出生長大
My parents are born and raised in taiwan,
我是在美國出生長大
And I was born and raised in the U.S.,
所以這裏面有很多的歷史
And so there's a lot of history
在我的身後有很深厚的文化
And a lot of culture behind who I am.
splendid
( A Whole New World歌詞，出自動畫片《阿拉丁》）
tell me, princess
now when did you last let your heart decide?
I can open your eyes
take you wonder by wonder
over, sideways, and under
on a magic carpet ride
a whole new world
你現在要去做什麼？
What are you about to do right now?
我馬上要出去
I'm about to go out here
去給一個扣籃大賽當評委
And judge this dunk contest.
這是最後的決賽，冠軍賽
This is the finale, the championship game,
為了耐克夏季聯賽
For the nike summer league,
所以我現在要去做這個了
So I'm about to get into this right now.
他們說我可以講中文
They said I could speak chinese.
林書豪！
Jeremy lin!
這裏的籃球文化很瘋狂
Basketball culture here is crazy.
球迷們很熱愛籃球
The fans, they love basketball.
這裏總有人在打籃球
There's people playing basketball
任何時間，在任何球場上
All the time on all the courts.
這裏的競賽水平絕對在提升
The level of competition is definitely growing.
能有機會看到這些比賽
Got a chance to see some games.
所以，你知道，這真是很棒的回歸
So, you know, it's definitely awesome coming back
而且還看到這項運動（籃球）在這個國家進步了這麼多
And seeing how much the sport has grown in the country.
準備，預備，開始！
Ready, set, go!
我想來到這裏
I just think coming here,
我看到了很多勤奮努力的人
I'm seeing a lot of really diligent, hard workers.
我感到所有人都很用功
I feel like everybody works very hard,
他們做了所有他們能做的事
And they do everything they can
就為了養活他們自己，還有他們的家人
To support themselves and their families,
對於我來說，籃球就是我養活自己和家人的方式
And for me, that way is basketball.
我認為勤奮這種精神是根深蒂固的
And I think hard work is definitely ingrained
在台灣文化裏，在中國文化裏
In taiwanese culture, in chinese culture.
所以，對我來說，那是一些
And so, for me, that's something
我試著去學會並且接受的東西
I try to pick up on and really embrace.
喲，兄弟，我們要出發啦
Yo, man, we gotta go.
書豪？
Jeremy?
在週五早上12點01分
At 12:01 Friday morning,
NBA停擺了所有的球員
The nba locked out its players
因為勞資雙方無法在新一輪的集體談判上達成一致
After failing to reach a new collective bargaining agreement.
停擺對很多人有巨大影響
The lockout has a very large impact on a lot of people.
目前放在談判桌上的條件
The current offer that is on the table
不是我們所能接受的
Is not one that we can accept.
停擺可能是幾個禮拜
It could be a couple weeks,
也可能是幾個月
Could be a couple months.
我們已經聽說
We're already hearing
這將是一個長期的停擺
This is gonna be a very long lockout.
我們將進入NBA的嚴冬
We're about to go into the nuclear winter of the nba.
勞資雙方的工資談判過程
The collective bargaining process
已經完全破裂
Has completely broken down.
我們都身處其中
We're all in this together.
如果這些球員不給他們
And if these players don't give them
想要的，他們是不會開工的
What they want, they're not going to play.
我不認為這個問題得到了解決
I don't think it's resolved.
我覺得這是個很糟的建議
I think it's bad advice.
我其實私下裏
I actually secretly
希望這次停擺能繼續
Wanted the lockout to continue,
因為這給了我額外的時間去提高
Because it gave me extra time to get better.
我們願意繼續談判
We are willing to continue discussions
基於一個有可能性的妥協的基礎上
On a potential compromise.
有一些老闆
There are some owners
願意走在這個賽季之前
Who are willing to forego the season.
我們想要打籃球
We want to play basketball.
那就是我們做的事
That's what we do,
現在，我們沒有一個機會
And right now, we don't have an opportunity
去球場上做我們最擅長的事
To go out and do what we do best.
如果整個賽季都沒了
If we need to lose an entire season,
那也只能這麼幹了
We should go ahead and do it.
我所有浸滿汗水的T恤都在這了
I got all my sweaty t-shirts in here, man.
那太噁心了
That's disgusting.
所以我知道停擺時間越長
So I knew the longer the lockout went,
我就會成為越出色的球員
The better player I would become.
我們在熱身
We're warming up.
我們只是在熱身
We're just warming up.
就是這樣，那一發很完美
Boom. That's it. That one was perfect.
感覺好嗎？
Feel good?
感覺很好
Feels good.
當他成為一個更好的投手
As he gets better as a shooter,
隨著時間過去，就像錢，錢，錢一樣
Over time it's gonna be like money, money, money.
他只會變得越來越好
He's only gonna get better,
而且他真的非常好，難道不是嗎？
And he's awfully good now, don't you think?
要進入他這個腦袋，那是另外一部分
That's the other part, getting into this cranium
讓他相信自己，就像我相信他一樣
To get him to believe like I believe in him.
聖誕快樂，籃球迷們
Merry christmas, basketball fans.
NBA重新開賽了
The nba is coming back.
球迷們就快得到他們夢寐以求的了
Fans are getting what they want.
老闆們和球員們達成了試行性的協議
Owners and players reached a tentative agreement
終結了149天的停擺
To end the 149-day lockout.
進入到我的第二年
Going into my second year,
我沒有
I'm not really, like,
去想任何讓我害怕的事情
Thinking about anything I'm afraid of.
你知道，我感覺，經歷了我的第一年
You know, I feel like through my first year,
至少在我眼中
At least in my own eyes,
我已經向自己證明，我能在這個水平打球
Like, I proved to myself that I can play at this level.
我想在心態上，我變得更好了
And I think mentally, I'm at a much better place
我能就這樣進去，然後做我自己
Where I'm just going in, and I'm just gonna be myself
打我自己的比賽
And play my own game,
從那個立場來看，我真的一點也不畏懼
And from that standpoint, I'm really not afraid
在進入訓練營後發生的事情
Of anything going into training camp.
我感覺我已經沒有什麼可以失去了
I feel like I have nothing to lose.
我們缺一個感到滿意的中鋒
We didn't have a center that we felt good about,
我們需要足夠的薪水空間
And we needed to create enough salary cap space
去招攬一個中鋒
To go make an offer,
為了這樣做，我們要裁掉一些球員
And in order to do so, we had to cut somebody.
這是我們做過的決定中
It was one of the hardest decisions
最艱難的決定之一
That we could have had to make.
他們中途給我打電話
They called me upmidway through
在訓練的中途
In the middle of a drill.
他們說，「嘿，你需要到樓上來一趟」
They're like, "hey, you got to go upstairs."
我走到樓上，然後總經理
I went in there, and the general manager
和助理總經理說，
And assistant general managerwere like,
「我們得裁掉你」
"we gotta let you go.
「我們想要德安德魯·喬丹」
We're trying to get deandre jordan."
他已經在賽季前付出了巨大的努力
He had worked tremendously hard pre-season,
所以我想，「天啊，這是一個大打擊啊」
o I was like, "man, this is a blow.
我的意思是，這就像一腳，剛好踢在你的肚子上
I mean, this is a kick in the stomach right here."
他們就像
They were like,
「哦，我們祝你好運」
"oh, we wish you the best of luck."
我說，「謝謝」
I was like, "thanks."
48小時後
Within 48 hours,
他被休斯敦火箭隊接收
He was picked up by the houston rockets.
是的，我們一直在希望
Yeah, we were hoping
沒有其他隊把他挑走
That no one else picked him up.
我們對他感興趣，已經有很長一段時間了
We were interested in him for quite a long time.
看過他在哈佛的比賽
Had been to his games at harvard.
那時候，我們就把他招進來，然後說
At the time, we just added him and said,
「嘿，讓他加入看看會發生什麼」
"hey, let's bring him in and see what happens."
我就去了休斯敦
I went to houston.
當時那裏有6個控衛
There were six point guards there.
我甚至沒法參加訓練
I couldn't even get reps in practice.
我不明白
I don't understand.
我在金州勇士隊是個候補控衛
I was backup point guard at golden state,
現在他們把我帶到這裏
And now they're gonna bring me here,
然後我成了第六根弦（吉他聲音最低的那根弦）？
And I'm sixth string?
林書豪在帶球
Jeremy lin on the drive.
把球帶到籃筐，然後上籃
Take it to the rim, lays it up.
在馬刺隊大個子球員面前的一個好球
Good shot with the spurs' bigs right in his face.
當火箭隊接收了他
When the rockets picked him up,
對於他來說，可能已經是跌入瓶底了
That was probably the bottom of the barrel for him.
一個週日晚上，我們在聯誼會上
Sunday night, we were in fellowship,
我記得林書豪說，「嘿，我得走了」
And I remember Jeremy said, "hey, I gotta go.
「我得趕飛機去休斯頓「
"I gotta catch my flight to Houston."
他當時站在門口
He was standing at the door,
他眼中含淚，因為……
And he had tears in his eyes, because, um...
因為壓力真的讓他難以承受
Because the pressure was really getting to him.
他不知道他的未來裏還有什麼
He just didn't know what his future was gonna hold.
我記得他轉向我，然後說
And I remember he turned to me and he says,
「我不知道我還能不能繼續撐下去」
"I don't know if I can keep doing this."
僅僅在火箭隊待了12天
After only 12 days with the rockets,
他再一次被裁
He was cut again.
那天正好是聖誕節
It was christmas day.
過去幾周顯然發生了很多事情
So obviously a lot has been happening the last couple of weeks.
你心裏在想什麼？
What's going through your mind,
你今天感覺怎麼樣？
And how you feeling today?
聖誕節早上，我被裁了
Christmas morning, I was waived.
聖誕夜，我坐飛機回家
Flew back home on christmas night,
兩周之內，我兩次被裁
And within two weeks, I had been waived twice
而裁掉我的兩個隊說他們還需要我
By two teams who said they still wanted me.
今天早上10點
10 a.M. This morning,
我得知紐約尼克斯隊選了我
Um, found out the knicks had picked me up.
馬上我將第一次為尼克斯隊上場
And that's gonna be my first game with the knicks.
在甲骨文球館（金州勇士隊主場，林書豪待的第一支NBA球隊）
It's gonna be at oracle arena.
這場比賽明天晚上就要打了
You know, I'm literally going into this game tomorrow night,
而我還完全不知道隊友有哪些人
I have no idea who my teammates are.
我從未和他們一起打過球
I've never played with them one time.
我完全不知道我們執行什麼戰術
I have no idea what plays we run.
球隊的一個戰術也不清楚
I don't know a single play,
甚至還沒和教練講過話
And, you know, I haven't even talked to the coach yet,
所以這下「好玩」了
So it's gonna be interesting.
林書豪要上場了
I see jeremy lin coming in.
他們（尼克斯）今天剛剛簽下他
They just signed him today.
只是在賽前的投籃練習稍微活動了一下
Went through a walk-through, at shoot-around today.
林去年在金州勇士隊打過寥寥幾場比賽
Lin, who played with golden state last year sparingly,
在發展聯盟也打過
Played in the d-league,
歡呼很熱烈
Gets a nice ovation.
這是我絕好的機會
It's a great opportunity for me
只要能打上球
To be able to just play,
現在對我來說
And I think, for me right now,
最重要的一件事
The one thing I really care about
就是這樣一個打球的機會
Is just an opportunity to play.
我將傾盡全力
I'm gonna give my best effort,
就算最終失敗
And, you know, if I go down,
我也要用我的方式證明自己
I'm gonna make sure I go down doing it my way,
同時，也是神的方式
Which is god's way.
所以比賽前一晚
So it's the night before,
我打包好了行李
And, you know, I gotta get my bags ready,
明天的比賽過後，我們將前往洛杉磯
And after the game tomorrow, we head to l.A.,
再來是薩克拉門托，然後將飛去紐約，一直待在那裏
Sacramento, and then I'm off to new york for good.
五場比賽過去了，我卻一分鐘都沒上
Five games go by, and I'm not playing at all.
我覺得這一切都說不通
Nothing was really making sense to me.
如果你簽了我
If you bring me in,
卻連球隊訓練也不讓我打
And you don't let me play in practice,
更不要說正式比賽了，那為什麼要我呢？
Let alone the games, then why am I here?
我當時覺得，我可以幫助你們
I felt like, you know, I could help you,
而只能眼睜睜地看著球隊輸球
And I was watching us lose.
尼克斯隊已經四連敗了
The knicks have lost four straight games.
連敗還在繼續
And the losing streak continues.
尼克斯隊已經六連敗了
Knicks have now lost six in a row.
尼克斯隊的場上沒有很好的化學反應
There's a chemistry problem there on the floor.
他們需要一個控衛來分配球
They need a point guard to distribute the ball.
林書豪最初的兩年合同
Jeremy's original two-year contract
即將到期
Was about to expire,
這意味著如果尼克斯隊裁掉他
Which meant that, if the knicks let him go,
他不僅得不到薪水，而且，將永遠失去機會
He'd be dropped with no pay, and, this time, for good.
在訓練時，書豪站在我旁邊
During practice, jeremy was standing right beside me
麥克·德安東尼
尼克斯2008-2012主教練
就站在場邊
On the side of the court
但沒有加入訓練
And not really get in even in practice.
我們把他簽下來只是
以防萬一哪天有人受傷時頂替的
He was just there in case one of these guys got hurt.
我已經隱約有預感了
I pretty much saw the writing on the wall.
當時就想，「差不多就是這樣了」
I was like, "I'm pretty much done,"
我只能接受現實
And, like, I was resigned to the fact
我又要被裁了
That I was gonna get let go.
站在場邊的時候，他走向我
Standing on the side of the court, he comes up to me,
他說，「嘿，教練，我有一個問題。」
And he goes, "hey, coach, I've got a question."
我就說，「書豪，什麼問題？」
I go, "what is it, jeremy?"
「我在這兒一直都是打出租車的」
"I'm taking a taxi everywhere.
「我應該把我的車帶過來嗎？」
Should I ship my car out here?"
當時他的反應是，「呃，也許不必」
And he was like, "uh, you know, probably not."
我當時就想，「完了，又要被裁了「
I was like, "oh, hell, I'm gonna get waived."
所以我就跟助教格蘭說
And so I went and talked to glen.
我說，「格蘭，你怎麼看？」
I said, "glen, what do you think?"
他說，「其實我們還沒有真正看過他打球」
And he goes, "well, we haven't really seen him.
「我們不清楚」
We don't know."
我說，「這樣吧，我們就讓他試試」
And I said, "you know what? Let me try to see
「如果週二之前讓他試著打幾場比賽」
"if we can get him in a couple games
「看看會發生什麼」
Before Tuesday and just see what happens."
他們對我說，「今晚你要上場」
They're like, "look, you're gonna play tonight.
「上場之後」
"I want you to go out there.
「不希望你做太多事情」
I don't want you to do too much."
我說，「好的，我不會的」
I was like, "okay, I won't."
加內特已經得了8分
8 points for garnett.
林書豪丟球，布拉德利斷球上籃得分
Lin coughs it up, bradley to the rim.
我真的沒有做很多事
I didn't do too much.
我幾乎什麼都沒做，我的表現糟透了
I pretty much did nothing, and I played horrible.
投籃不中
You know, I missed shots,
又是失誤，又是犯規
I had turnovers, I had bad fouls.
林書豪犯規
Lin reached in.
我想，我最多還有一次機會
I thought, at most,
就是下一場比賽
I had one more chance the next game.
我當時想，我剛剛搞砸了和波士頓的比賽
I was like, "okay, I just screwed the boston game.
「也許我要被裁了」
"I probably will get cut,
「但他們明天可能會再給我一次機會」
But they may give me one more chance tomorrow."
我記得那時
I think at the time,
書豪其實住在他紐約的哥哥那
Jeremy was actually staying with his brother in new york,
而在飛機上他跟我說
And he was talking to me on the plane.
蘭德裏·菲爾茲
後衛，尼克斯2010-2012
今晚會有一些朋友在我哥那過夜
He's like, "you know, my brother, he's got some people over,
所以，我可不可以
"um, so, you know, is it cool
在你家睡一晚上？
If I crash at your place instead?"
我說，「當然可以」
You know, I was like, "yeah, sure, man, you can come."
不過我也有提醒他
I was giving him forewarning, though,
我的沙發不太大
That my couch wasn't huge.
那個沙發是租來的
It was actually a rental couch at the time.
差不多只有六英尺（183厘米）長
It might have been maybe six feet long.
我們大概凌晨2點才到
We get in at, like, 2:00 in the morning.
我去了菲爾茲家
I go over to landry's place.
他給我看了他的沙發
He's like, "this is my couch,"
大概這麼大
And his couch is like this big.
我當時就無語了
I'm like, "dude."
我只能把頭掛在沙發一頭
I have my head hanging off of one end
雙腳掛在另外一頭
And my legs hanging off the other.
這樣怎麼能睡得好呢？
I'm like, "oh, my gosh, how am I gonna get a good night's rest?"
明天還要打球
Like, "I might play tomorrow.
這也許是我最後的機會
This might be my last chance."
我記得當時對自己說
I remember thinking to myself,
第一，我希望他能上場
One, I hope he gets in,
因為他在波士頓的糟糕表現
Because he really didn't do enough in the boston game
無法保證他有足夠的上場時間
To warrant getting big minutes.
第二，如果他上場，他必須有好的表現
And, two, if he gets in, he's gotta play well,
不然這場比賽過後他們就會裁了他
Or they're gonna release him after the game.
有趣的是
It's funny.
本賽季是上次停擺後11、12年內
This season was the only season in the
last, like, 11, 12 years since the last lockout
唯一有連著三場背靠背的賽季
where people have played back-to-back-to-back games.
而尼克斯隊只有一次連著三場背靠背
And new york only had one stretch of back-to-back-to-back games.
如果當時有更多休息時間
And if we had more days to rest,
我不確定那場比賽我能否上場
I'm not sure if I would have been able to play in that game.
那天我禱告了
I prayed that day,
我的禱告是
And my prayer is,
「神啊，如果讓他打NBA是你的意願」
"god, if this is your will for him to play nba,
「那麼你需要展現給他看」
You need to show it."
莫羅再次得分
There's morrow. Morrow knocks it down.
德隆投籃
Williams sets himself,
三分命中
Puts up the 3, and knocks that one down.
尼克斯隊已經落後10分了
The knicks find themselves down by 10 already.
尼克斯隊的山姆波特，個人第二次犯規
New york foul is on shumpert, his second.
看看誰要上場了
Again, mike, look who's coming in.
是林書豪，你可以聽到球迷的大聲歡呼
Jeremy lin, and you hear a pretty big ovation.
他看起來沒有猶豫
He didn't look tentative,
也沒有過於憂慮
He didn't look overly concerned.
他看起來就像在說，「我要放手一搏了」
He looked like, "dude, I'm about to go do it.
如果他們裁了我就裁吧
"if they cut me, they cut me.
就算我再也不能在NBA打球也無所謂了
"if I don't never play another nba game, so be it.
我要讓你們看看真正的林書豪是怎麼打球的
I'm going to play like jeremy lin can play."
林書豪突破上籃
Jeremy lin drives and finishes.
漂亮的上籃得分
Nice play from lin.
丟球了
There's a strip of it.
林書豪長傳給道格拉斯
Lin throws it ahead to toney douglas.
擦板得分
Up for the layup! Banks it in!
山姆波特殺過來了，傳球給林
Here comes shumpert to lin.
林上籃，球進了
Lin flips it up and puts it in.
又是林書豪！
Jeremy lin once again!
他的半場數據差不多是10+4+4
He finished the half with like 10, 4, and 4,
對半場來說很不錯了
Like, good numbers for a half.
超過了他之前所做的一切
That was such a higher high than, like, anything he's, like, done.
我當時欣喜若狂
So I was, like, ecstatic at that point.
而到了下半場，他簡直
The second half, he just went...
簡直瘋了
He just went nuts.
（林書豪）突到籃下了，球又進了
Driving to the basket, does it again.
同時有加罰的機會
He's got a chance for a 3-point play as he got hit.
（林書豪）撞到佩特洛，又殺向籃筐了
Bumped by petro, gets to the rim.
進球有效，還造成對手犯規
Count it and a foul!
林書豪！
Jeremy lin!
他經歷了美妙的一晚
He has in one special night
成了（麥迪遜廣場）花園的寵兒
Become a garden favorite.
今晚會被人記住嗎？
Will it be remembered?
他連著做了
He was stringing together,
三個胯下運球
Like, three crossover moves in a row.
過去他從未這樣做過
Like, things he's never done before.
（林書豪）再次撕開防守
Splits the defense again!
殺到籃下了！上籃命中！
Gets to the rim! Pops it in!
還造成犯規！哇！
And a foul! Wow!
球迷已經都坐不住了
And the crowd on their feet
站起來向這個男人致敬
Paying homage to this man.
看起來連他的隊友們
Clyde, even it looks like his teammates
也不相信所發生的一切
Don't believe what they're seeing.
我當時太興奮了
I was just so emotional.
現在他們不能把我裁掉了
There's no way they can cut me now.
我剛剛打了生命中最重要的比賽
I just had the game of my life.
又是一個胯下運球後殺向籃筐
Again, the crossover, the basket.
投籃，又進了
Puts it up, pops it in!
林書豪，25分！
Jeremy lin with 25!
球迷們已經瘋狂了！
And this crowd is going crazy!
盡情地突破，玩弄
Penetrating, manipulating,
完全摧毀了籃網隊
Devastating the nets!
他是來自哈佛的英雄
He's the hero from harvard,
尼克斯隊終於
As the knicks
拿到了一場亟需的勝利，這是他生命中最重要的比賽
Get a much-needed victory on the game of his life.
他已經被興奮的隊友包圍
And he is swarmed by his ecstatic teammates
還有麥迪遜廣場花園興奮的球迷
And a jubilant crowd here at madison square garden.
感謝神
I'm just thankful to god
賜予我這次上場的機會
For this opportunity to be able to come out here
來為這支球隊打球
And play with this team and this organization.
我洗了個澡
Man, I was taking a shower,
我甚至分不清
And I was like... I didn't even know.
那是洗澡水
I was like, "is this water, like, from the shower,
還是我流下的喜悅的淚水
Or am I actually crying, like, tears of joy?"
我實在是太興奮了
Oh, I was just, like, so high on emotion.
我太開心了，我就坐在浴室裏
I was so happy. I was sitting in the shower,
腦子裏在回放發展聯盟裏的那些時光
Replaying all the times in the d-league,
那些我不得不經歷的
All these flashbacks of these tough times
艱苦歲月的片斷
I had to go through.
我記得我出來後
And I remember I got out,
看到我的家人，他們都在微笑
I saw my family, and they were all smiling.
我打電話給經紀人
I called my agent,
他在對我大喊大叫
And he was yelling at me on the phone, you know, like,
他說，「我太為你驕傲了！我就知道你行的」
"I'm so proud of you. I knew you could do it."
這就是我希望取得的突破
That was kind of like the much-needed breakthrough that I was hoping for.
在林書豪取得對籃網隊的驚艷表現之前
Before jeremy lin's first big game against new jersey,
他根本不在尼克斯隊的計劃之內
He really wasn't in the knicks' plans at that point,
據我所知
And I'm told they had begun
他們當時已經考慮換掉他了
To look seriously at replacements.
週六晚上的麥迪遜廣場花園
Clyde, Saturday night, madison square garden
和整個賽季一樣人聲鼎沸
Sounded as loud as we've heard it all season.
他無與倫比
He was magnificent.
從尼克斯隊的角度
You just hope from a knicks standpoint
你會希望他能引領進攻
That he can run the offense
保持週六那樣的精彩表現
As well as he ran it on Saturday.
第一次首發我其實沒有特別緊張
I just really wasn't nervous for my first start.
通常來說，我應該會緊張
And, you know, usually, I would be,
但不知道為什麼我感覺很舒服
But I don't know why I just felt really comfortable,
超出自然的平靜
And it was just a supernatural peace,
這就是一些我無法解釋的事情
And it's one of those things that, you know, I can't really explain.
林書豪的第一次NBA首發出場
For jeremy's first nba start,
阿瑪爾·斯塔德邁爾因個人原因缺陣
Amar'e stoudemire was out for personal reasons,
卡梅隆·安東尼上半場因傷下場
And carmelo anthony suffered an injury in the first half.
安東尼走路很艱難
Carmelo anthony comes up hobbling.
他很難受
He's in a lot of discomfort.
他現在已經不能走路了
He can't move right now.
尼克斯隊現在需要一位領袖
The knicks desperately needed a leader,
而林書豪將承擔起這個使命
And jeremy would answer the call.
林書豪繞過傑弗森
Lin gets around jefferson,
還在看人，上反籃得分
Looking, and backs it in.
上場比賽有不少這樣的表現
He had a couple of those the other night.
我們不斷地打擋拆
We were running pick and roll
一個擋拆接一個擋拆
After pick and roll after pick and roll.
林書豪傳給裏面的傑弗裏斯
Lin inside to jeffries!
我不知道他能否保持對籃網那場的表現
I didn't know how he would follow up, that new jersey game,
因為那場實在太棒了
'Cause it was such a high,
但是（本場比賽）他不斷上演各種誇張的上籃
But he just kept making ridiculous layups,
各種跳投命中
He was hitting jumpers.
他們不瞭解我的打球習慣
They didn't know my tendencies,
他們不知道我的弱點
They didn't know my weak spots,
也不知道我的優勢和最佳投籃點
My strong spots, my sweet spots.
林書豪突進來了
Lin on the drive,
拉桿，命中！
Flips it up, drops it in!
同時造成犯規！好一個反手上籃！
And a foul! Reverse layup!
他們從未看過我打球
They had never seen me play.
向前推進，傳給山姆波特，又回傳給林書豪
Pushing it, ahead to shumpert, back to lin.
林被打到了，球還是放進，2+1！
Lin gets hit, puts it in, and a foul!
上籃
Lays it up, puts it up,
還是活球
Chandler keeps it alive.
林必須得投了
lin has to put it up.
在進攻24秒結束前三分命中
A 3-pointer as the shot clock expired!
我像壓榨秘書似的使用他
I'm riding him like friggin' secretariat.
林書豪
Jeremy lin
連續兩個職業生涯的重要夜晚
With his second consecutive career night.
他現在是尼克斯隊新的首發控衛
He is the new starting point guard of the knicks.
尼克斯隊再次取勝
And the knicks win again.
全場觀眾起立向林書豪致敬
A standing ovation for jeremy lin.
過程中有非常多細微的因素
You know, there's so many little variables
是我無法掌控的
With every step of the way being something I can't control.
比如，休斯頓火箭隊晚了一天才裁掉我
You know, houston waives me a day late.
如果他們早一天裁掉我
If they waive me a day earlier,
就會超過裁人的線
I would have been past the waiver wire.
那天早上山姆波特正好受傷
Shumpert gets hurt that morning.
尼克斯隊才選了我
The knicks pick me up,
因為去年他們試訓過我
Because they had worked me out the year before.
正好，尼克斯隊的主教練是德安東尼
You know, it happens to be d'antoni who's coaching here
他的進攻體系就像是為我量身打造的
Whose offense is tailor-made for me.
突然之間，一切都變得瘋狂了
And all of a sudden, things just go crazy.
過去兩場他平均得分26.5分
He's averaging 26 1/2 points a game the last two games.
我認為這不可持續
I don't think that's gonna continue.
這顯然無法持續
Obviously, that's not gonna continue.
接著我們踏上客場之旅，前往華盛頓
Then we hit the road and go to washington,
又將遇上約翰·沃爾
And it's like john wall again, you know.
夏季聯賽的時候我和沃爾交過手
Like, I played against john wall in the summer league,
現在狹路相逢
And now it's, like, a rematch.
又要和他對位
Now I'm playing against him again.
嗚~
Ooh!
林書豪突破到禁區內
Lin on the drive, gets inside.
林書豪反手上籃，漂亮！
Reverse layup. Great play by jeremy lin.
沃爾殺過來了，看著
Here comes wall. Look at wall.
撕開防守
Breaks the press,
左手暴扣
And throws it down with the left hand!
我當時的反應是，靠，他居然在我頭上扣籃
I was like, "dang, he kinda dunked on my head."
我必須還以顏色！
I was like, "I'm gonna try to get him back."
幾個回合過後，他們的防守出了問題
Couple possessions later, they messed up their coverage,
我輕鬆地突進去
I had a free lane,
就試著去扣扣籃
And I just tried to take the rim down.
林書豪突破！
Lin drives!
這才是你說的扣籃
There's the dunk you're talking about, clyde.
林書豪點燃球迷的激情
Jeremy lin fires up the crowd.
我看到這麼大的空當
When I saw that opening,
我只是用盡全力去完成那記扣籃
I just tried to dunk it as hard as I could.
我不知道
I don't know. There's just...
只是有太多的痛苦和磨煉
There's been so much pain and so many trying times,
現在終於能打上球了
And now that I get to play,
我只是想把這些都宣洩出來
I'm just letting it all out, man.
把一切都宣洩在球場上
I'm just letting it all out on the floor.
比賽過後，當我回想時
After the game, I just look back,
覺得很有趣
And I'm like, "man, that was so fun."
一個美妙的故事正在醞釀，主角是林書豪
The great story that's brewing is jeremy lin,
他本年度的合同算是有保證了
And this week, contracts are guaranteed for the rest of the year.
他的球場表現就像在說，「讓他的價值充分展現」
（電影《甜心先生》的台詞）
He's been balling out, saying, "show that man his money."
有一點可以肯定，他在場上的視野很好
The things that's for real is his vision,
這不會變
Which won't change,
他的速度不會變
His speed, which won't change,
他對比賽的認知不會變
His knowledge of the game, which won't change.
我就是覺得不會變
I just don't see it changing.
請不要再引用我的話了
Now, again, please don't quote me on that one.
肯尼·史密斯：現在他該出現在球探報告裏了
Kenny Smith: Now he's on the scouting report.
沙奎爾·奧尼爾： 是的，當然
Shaquille o'neal: Yeah, he is now.
我們來看看他是否在洛杉磯湖人隊的球探報告裏
Let's see if he's in the scouting report for the lakers
沒錯，週五晚上，關注麥迪遜廣場花園
Oh, yeah, he is. On Friday night at the garden.
過去兩周我就是睡這裏的
This is basically where I lived the last two weeks
睡在這張沙發上
And so it's the couch I slept on.
我的哥哥和大嫂
Uh, my brother and sister-in-law,
好好地招待了我
Uh, did a good job of hosting me.
很開心
Had a lot of fun.
現在他們的小弟弟就要搬出去了
And now their little kid might have to move out.
如果我現在不洗衣服
If I don't do laundry now,
那我結婚了也不會洗，沒錯
I won't do laundry when I'm married. Fact.
大嫂：你們髒死了
Sister-in-law:You guys are brats.
我們會做別的事情
So? We do other things.
大嫂：比如？
Sister-in-law: Like what?
什麼比如不比如的
What do you mean, like what?
你應該問有什麼是我們不做的
Like, what don't we do, is the question.
大嫂：那你會做什麼？
Sister-in-law: What do you do?
媽媽： 你 會做什麼？
Shirley: What do you do?
我每天都午睡
I take a nap every day.
媽媽：是的，這個我瞭解
Shirley: Yeah, that I know.
沒有很多人能做到這個
Who does that? Not many people can.
沒有很多人可以
Not many people can.
你還是個吃貨
And you eat a lot,
一天到晚吃個不停
Nonstop all day long. Yeah.
昨天，總經理跟我說
Yesterday, the general manager was like,
書豪，你的合同有保障了
"hey, jeremy, by the way, you're guaranteed now,
不要睡沙發了
So get off the couch."
我......
I was like...
媽媽：他其實有地方住
Shirley: This guy has a place to stay,
但是他不想住那
But he doesn't want to stay there.
只想賴在這裏
He want to crash in here.
他們可不想這個上新聞
They don't want this to be on the news,
林書豪睡在他哥哥的沙發上
Jeremy sleeping on the couch at his brother's.
為什麼？
Why?
這太瘋狂了
It's crazy.
太瘋狂了
It's just crazy to...
告訴你吧，我的社交網絡，我的手機
I'm telling you, social media, Twitter, facebook, my phone, it's just...
我不知道還能不能更瘋狂
I don't know if it could get crazier than this.
我真的不知道
Like, I really don't.
林書豪？
Jeremy lin?
有聽說過嗎？
Are you following that story at all?
不知道，聽過一下
No idea. I know who he is,
但我真的不太清楚狀況
But I don't really know what's going on too much with that.
你對林書豪過去一周的表現感到震驚嗎？
Are you surprised at the production that lin's had over the past week?
我還不知道他做過什麼
I don't even know what he's done.
根本就不知道你們說的是哪個人
Like, I have no idea which you guys are talking about.
我看了一些報道
I'm reading all these quotes
關於他（科比）說了什麼
About what he's saying.
「科比完全不知道林書豪是何人」
"kobe bryant has no idea who jeremy lin is."
我的反應是，「什麼」？
I'm like, "what?"
我在想，「你為什麼要這麼說」
I'm like, "why would you do that?
「我完全沒有談論你」
"I didn't say anything about you.
「從沒說過你的壞話」
I never talked bad about you."
所以聽說這件事時，我心想……
So when I heard that, I was like...
「球場上見」
"here we go."
你會單防他嗎？
Would you consider guarding him
如果他的表現很好？
If he's having one of those games?
你們不要著急
Let's not get ahead of ourselves here.
加油！
Let's go!
新的英雄已經出現
There is a new man in town.
狹路相逢勇者勝
"may the best man lin(win)."
今晚的競猜，林書豪能否超過23分
Over-under, 23 points for lin tonight, bomani.
對手是內線長人如林的湖人隊
Against the lakers with those trees they've got inside?
今晚不會有那麼多林瘋狂時刻了
It won't be so linsane tonight.
今晚誰得分高？科比還是林書豪？
Kobe or lin? Who scores more tonight?
我選林書豪，我的英雄
I'm going with my guy, jeremy lin, my hero.
因為他無所不「林」
Because all he does is lin, baby!
短短一周
Jeremy lin in just one week
林書豪就改變了一切
Has turned things around
無論對他自己還是尼克斯隊來說
For his career and for the new york knicks.
我愛林書豪，太棒了！
I love it! It's awesome, man!
這是紐約發生過最美妙的事情
This is like the greatest thing that's happened to new york ever.
就是這麼一個夜晚
It's one of those nights,
一個故事
And it's one of those stories
讓我們知道為何如此熱愛體育
Where it really is why we love sports.
我不知道結果會怎樣
I didn't know how it was gonna turn out,
但是
But I was like,
我將非常非常具有攻擊性
"I'm just gonna be really, really aggressive."
我們的比賽進行得很順利，投籃都彈無虛發
Everything was going well, everything was going down.
林書豪跳投，命中！
Lin puts it up, puts it in!
完美的開局
Terrific start!
聽聽球迷的歡呼吧！
And listen to this garden crowd.
我記最讓我激動不已的是
I think the one thing where I kind of lost it a little bit,
看著他帶球，突然急停轉身
He'd come down, he kind of like stutter-stepped, and spun
手指很柔軟地輕輕一投
And finger-rolled it.
林喜歡這個大空當
Lin likes the open floor.
轉身，投籃，命中！
Spinning, puts it up and puts it in!
林書豪，超級精彩的得分
Sensational play for jeremy lin!
整個球館都沸騰了，在這樣一個全國矚目的舞台
The garden erupted, and to do it on the national stage,
任何人看過之後都永生難忘
Anybody who saw that moment will never forget.
又一次點燃了麥迪遜廣場花園
Electrifying the garden again!
他已經得了18分了
He's got 18 points.
歡迎來到演播室，這是林書豪的半場個人表演
Welcome to our studios for the jeremy lin toyota halftime show.
林書豪是頂級的
Jeremy lin was superb,
投籃12中7
7 of 12 from the field,
拿下18分5次助攻
18 points, 5 assists.
科比和他的隊友的投籃手感還很差
Kobe bryant and the lakers struggling shooting the ball,
但現在他們還只落後8分
But they're only down by 8.
科比，一系列假動作
Bryant, a couple of fakes,
要投籃了，球進了
Gonna put it up, and knocks it down.
林書豪搶斷
Stripped by lin, stolen by lin.
助攻左側的山姆波特，左手上籃命中！
Left side, shumpert, left-handed layup!
科比轉身，高難度的一球
Bryant spinning, difficult shot.
又是科比
Kobe bryant again.
他要開始接管比賽了
He is starting to get in one of those zones right now.
加索爾在防守林書豪
Gasol is on lin.
一個兩分球，進了！
Puts up the 2-pointer. Puts it in!
林書豪31分！
Jeremy lin with 31!
傑弗裏斯搶下籃板
And the rebound by jeffries.
林書豪三分
Lin for 3.
梆！
Bang!
三分命中
3-pointer!
林書豪！
Jeremy lin!
我整年最喜歡的一次得分
And my favorite play of this whole year
就是那個底腳的三分
Was when I hit that 3 in the corner
因為那場比賽有太多的渲染
Just because that game had so much hype,
那記投籃就像一把匕首
And that shot was kind of the dagger
狠狠地給了他們一刀
That put the game out of reach for them.
本賽季兩次被裁
Already cut twice this season,
因為無處可去而只能睡在隊友的沙發上
Sleeping on a teammate's couch, because he had nowhere else to go,
而一夜之間，他成了曼哈頓的寵兒
And, suddenly, jeremy lin is the toast of manhattan.
就在這裏
This is it right here.
這就是我的夢想
This is my dream, and, uh,
我感謝神
I'm just thankful to god, man,
讓我美夢成真
Because this is my dream being lived out,
我無比感恩
And I'm so thankful for that.
林書豪38分
Jeremy lin, 38 points.
本賽季尼克斯隊球員的得分新高
It's the most by a knick this season.
「林瘋狂」還在麥迪遜廣場花園繼續
Linsanity continues here in madison square garden.
這真的難以形容
It's indescribable, really.
我從未見過這樣的事情
It's something I've never seen before.
我沒有預料到
I didn't foresee this coming.
難以置信
You know, it's unbelievable.
我這人會很奇怪
This is, like, how weird I am.
我當時想這場比賽之後我要出口氣
I was like, "I'm gonna go off this game,"
採訪結束時，他們肯定會問我
And at the end of the interview, they're gonna be like,
你覺得科比現在認識你了嗎？
"oh, so do you think kobe knows who you are now?"
書豪，你知道肯定有個人會問你這個問題
Jeremy, you knew somebody was gonna ask you this,
你認為科比現在認識你了嗎？
But do you think kobe knows who you are now?
如果他們問我那個問題
If they ask me that question,
我的回答會是，「科比？誰啊？」
I'm gonna be like, "who the hell is kobe?"
我本想這樣回答
That's what I was gonna say.
但我想了一會兒
And then I, like, thought about it,
禱告的時候
And I prayed about it,
想想神會怎麼做呢？
I was like, you know, "what would jesus do?"
不，神應該不會這麼說
And I'm like, "jesus probably wouldn't say that,"
所以我要改變我的答案
So I was like, "I'm gonna change my answer."
「這得問科比本人了」
Aw, well, you guys have to ask kobe.
我不知道
I don't know.
讓我們來看看當今體育界最大的新聞：林書豪
Let's get to what matters in sports today, jeremy lin.
林書豪現在是紐約的第一巨星
Right now, the biggest star in new york is jeremy lin.
就算你不關注體育也一定聽過他的故事
I don't even think you have to
be a sports fan to hear about this story.
「林旋風」橫掃紐約全城
New york has a raging case of linsanity.
現在是瘋狂的時刻
That's what it is right now. It's madness right now.
林書豪
Jeremy lin!
無所不「林」
All I do is lin, lin, lin.
你覺得怎麼樣？
What do you think?
你覺得現在的一切如何？
What do you think about all this?
瘋狂，太瘋狂了
Um, it's crazy. It's just crazy.
現在體育界最大的頭條
One of the biggest headlines
就是「林瘋狂」
In sports right now is linsanity.
你還沒聽說過他？你會的
If you haven't caught it yet, you will.
「林瘋狂」席捲紐約城
Linsanity takes new york by storm.
他實在是尼克斯隊沒有辦法的辦法了
He was a last-ditch effort for the knicks.
當時的情況可能是，有人說，「今晚誰想上場嗎？」
They sort of said, "all right, who wants to play?"
他舉起了手，然後就有人說，「那好，你上吧」
And he raised his hand and, "all right, get in there."
我這麼多年報道體育以來前所未聞的事情
I have never seen anything like this in all my years of covering sports.
從為見過一個人從默默無聞
I've never seen somebody go from a no-name
在兩周之內成為一個轟動的現象
To an absolute phenomenon inside of two weeks.
太難以置信了
It's unbelievable.
他有魅力、有型、有天賦
He's doing it with charisma, with style, with flair,
而且，他還打得很開心
And he's having fun.
這很瘋狂，火得不行
It's crazy. It's catching fire.
我覺得「林瘋狂」這個詞
Linsanity, I think it'll probably be
將會收錄到下一版的字典裏
In the dictionary in the next version.
林瘋狂？我愛林瘋狂
Linsanity? I love it.
我愛林瘋狂，我為他感到高興
I love linsanity. I'm so happy for him.
林書豪（過去三場）得了89分
Jeremy lin's 89 points,
這是所有球員自NBA和ABA合併以來
職業生涯前三場首發合計最高分
The most by any player in his first
three pro starts since the aba-nba merger.
傳給外面的林，林面對裏德諾胯下運球
Outside to lin, crosses over ridnour,
投籃命中
And hits.
林書豪空中連線菲爾茲
Jeremy lin up top to fields.
林迅速殺到籃下
Lin a whirling dervish right to the rim,
左右騰挪完成上籃
Zigzagging to the cup.
尼克斯隊又取得一場勝利
The knicks have stolen one.
賽季最長的五連勝
It's their fifth straight win, their longest of the season.
您已經不是哈佛最有名的畢業生了
You have been surpassed as the most
famous person who is a harvard graduate.
我其實比你們更早知道林書豪
I knew about jeremy before you did.
您的意思是「林瘋狂」也有您的功勞？
Are you taking credit for linsanity?
我覺得您有點這個意思
It kind of feels like you are a little bit.
我並沒有功勞
I can't take credit for it,
我的意思只是，我比你們更早認識了他
But I'm just saying I was there early.
如你所說，這是很棒的故事
As you said, it's a great story.
對你來說，哪一部分最棒？
What's the greatest part in it for you?
我們取得五連勝
That we've won five in a row.
對我個人來說是這樣
That's it for me.
所有的一切
Uh, just everything,
這就是體育的魅力
Just here's just what's right with sports.
從默默無聞到一舉成名
He's an underdog that came up.
他很好地做到了
He does it the right way.
他夠格打NBA嗎？當然，毫無疑問
Can he play in the nba? Yeah, of course.
他全面，打得也很好
He's got all the tools, and he's playing really well.
那不是僥倖，他有實力
That's not a fluke, how he's playing.
當時場邊有個人
I had this one dude courtside
整場比賽都在對我大吼大叫
Who was just yelling at me the whole game.
「你只能持續一周罷了」
He's like, "you're a one-week wonder."
「這場比賽你就會輸了，你遜斃了」
You know, "you're not gonna win this game. You suck."
我們那場打得很糟糕
We were playing bad.
全隊都很疲憊
We were tired, and I was like,
「這將是一場艱難的比賽」
"man, this is gonna be a tough one to pull out."
比賽剩一分鐘時我們還落後五分
We were down 5 with a minute left.
那是一次關鍵的搶斷
You know, we got this huge steal,
扣籃，還落後三分
Layup, down 3.
他們進攻沒打成，我們有喘息的機會
They're coming down, we get a stop.
阿米爾·約翰遜那個加罰球
The and-1 at amir johnson
拉平了比分，他個人已有5個蓋帽
who I believe had 5 blocks to that point, ties the game.
林書豪假投三分，改為突破
Lin fakes the 3, drives,
突進去上籃了
Goes in for the layup,
球進了，還造成犯規！
It's good, and a foul!
林書豪有機會通過罰球扳平比分
Lin can tie it with a free throw.
當時球沒進
They come down, missed shot,
我們拿到球，比賽差不多還有20秒
And now we got the ball with, like, 20 seconds left.
林傳給山姆波特
Lin to shumpert,
山姆波特跳投
Shumpert, pull-up jump shot.
沒進，錢德勒搶到籃板
Won't go, Chandler the rebound.
尼克斯隊將耗盡時間，完成最後一投
And the knicks will hold it for the final shot
24秒進攻倒計時已經關閉
As the 24-second clock is shut off.
德安東尼沒有叫暫停
Mike d'antoni won't call time out
猛龍隊做好了防守準備
And let the raptors set up their d.
加拿大航空中心的觀眾都站起來了
The crowd on its feet here at the air canada centre.
林書豪跳投
Lin puts it up.
梆！！
Bang!
林書豪，三分命中！
Jeremy lin from downtown,
尼克斯隊取得領先！
And the knicks take the lead!
太驚人了！
Amazing here at the air canada centre!
只剩10秒鐘，所有人都站起來了
10 seconds, everyone standing,
全場有2萬人
20,000 in toronto.
拉開拉開！
Get out of his way!
讓他單挑卡爾德隆！
Let him just take calderon himself!
還剩3秒鐘，林書豪有身高優勢
Three seconds, lin sizes him up,
干拔三分命中！
Straightaway 3, buries it!
只留下0.5秒鐘
.5 remaining!
「林瘋狂」還在繼續！
Linsanity continues!
我對結果很滿意
I'm just glad it went like this,
讓林瘋狂能夠稍微冷卻一點
So we can calm the linsanity down a little bit.
我們無法阻擋
Where we couldn't get a stop...
我夢寐以求的，就是投進這樣的制勝球
That's all I dream about is hitting the game winner
再擺出搞怪的動作
And then doing some cool little dorky pose
然後帥氣地走回去
And then walking off.
像我小時候那樣
You know, that's, like, all I did growing up.
我一直想這麼做
I always wanted to do that.
想知道那是什麼感覺
I wanted to know what that felt like.
他有能力
He's got the game,
他態度很好，他很拉風
He's got the attitude, he's got the swag.
他什麼都有
He's got all of that.
謝謝你們
Okay. "thank you for being..."
或者我直接開始第一部分？
Or do I just do the first part?
可以
Yeah. Okay.
嘿，書豪，呃，我是說.......
"hey, jeremy..."I mean...Whoops.
it's driving me out of my mind
（Bell Biv Devoe《Poison》的歌詞）
只要撥打電話
"just dial star-star-knicks on your iphone or android phone..."
或登錄尼克斯隊官網
Or go to nyknicks.
can't get it outta my head
head
that girl is poison
天啊
Oh, man.
完美
Perfect.
所有印度尼西亞的朋友
"to all my friends in indonesia..."
所有新加坡的球迷
"to all my fans in singapore..."
全世界的球迷
"to all my fans around the world,
謝謝你們的支持
Thank you for all your support."
林瘋狂的魅力甚至繞過半個地球到了台灣
Linsanity is catching on even halfway around the world in taiwan,
點燃了台灣球迷的激情
Even halfway around the world in taiwan,Igniting a crowd in taipei that went to a bar
他們在早上8點鐘去酒吧看他的比賽
At 8:00 in the morning to watch him on tv.
（葡萄牙語）
（日語）
（西班牙語）
他把一切都處理得很好
He's handled everything very well,
像你說的，鎮定自若
As you said, unflappable,
如果還要挑刺的話
（chink in the armor：俗語，帶有對中國人的嘲諷意味）
But if there is a chink in the armor,
他還應該在哪些方面提高？
Where can lin improve his game?
Chink in the armor...
a chink in the armor...
很強壯，臂展很長
Nice build, he's got long arms.
這是一個合格控衛需要具備的
That's what you need as a point guard.
他實在是
And he's really, I mean...
他的眼神呢？（暗諷亞洲人的眼睛小）
What about his eyes?
迷離
Dreamy.
他的視野很好
He has great court vision.
如果不用Lin做雙關語
Take away the lin puns...Mm-hmm.
結果是這樣的
This is what you end up with.
令人驚「亞」
（"Amasian": amazing和asian的合體）
"amasian."
這......
now is that even...now is that even...
這合法嗎？
now is that even...Is that even legal?
是的，這是林書豪
Jeremy lin. Yes, that's real.
他是從幸運餅乾里蹦出來的
（幸運餅乾：美國中餐廳常見食品）
Jeremy lin coming out of a fortune cookie.
這一切證明我們是多麼措手不及
This whole thing has shown how unprepared
來面對這種文化
We were to deal with this culture in this context.
Floyd Mayweather（黑人拳擊手）在推特上評論林書豪說
Floyd mayweather on jeremy lin tweets...
這些炒作不過因為他是亞裔
"all the hype is because he's asian.
黑人球員每晚都有他那樣的表現
"black players do what he does every night
卻沒有得到同等的稱讚
And don't get the same praise."
首先，我認為他的話是種族歧視
First of all, what he said I think is racist.
他不但可以在NBA立足
Not only can he compete and make it in the nba,
他還不斷創造紀錄
The guy's tearing it up and is breaking records, you knucklehead.
看看這張圖，他用數學取得勝利
Check it out. "he does the math to win."
沒錯
yeah.
我們對亞裔的很多觀念根深蒂固
For many years, we've had many stereotypes about asian-americans,
現在一窩蜂全出來了
我們還都覺得這些都是小意思
And now they're all kind of coming
out like they're no big deal.
它們很要緊
They are a big deal.
這一天終於來了
And that'll do it.
（尼克斯隊）的連勝終止
The winning streak comes to an end
以令人失望的方式
In disappointing fashion,
新奧爾良黃蜂隊
As the new orleans hornets
讓林書豪和尼克斯隊吞下
林書豪時代以來第一場失利的苦果
Hand jeremy lin and the knicks their first loss in the jeremy lin era.
現在變得更簡單了
Now it's easier for me, you know.
如果有人說了種族歧視的話
Someone will say something racist,
我會一笑而過，覺得很有趣
And I'll laugh, and I'll think it's funny.
我會把所有負面的東西
Everything I get now, like, all the negative stuff,
都放到一個地方
I'll just put it in one place
然後把它們變成積極的東西
And turn it into positive stuff
讓我正確地使用
So that I could use it the right way,
當我帶著憤怒打球，我就會打得很爛
And when I play out of anger, I play horrible.
所以我學會控制自己的情緒
And so I had to learn how to control my emotions
然後讓它隨風而去
And then just, like, let it go.
手不要受傷
Don't break your hand.
你知道嗎？尼克斯隊的林書豪
So did you know that new knicks sensation, jeremy lin,
還有一個弟弟現在才大一，也打控衛
Has a brother who's a freshman point guard
好像是漢密爾頓學院
For hamilton college?
我們當然知道，不過就算不知道
We did, though even we didn't know
在今天的分區決賽上
That today's continental home finale
我們看到林書豪的整個家庭都來了
Would bring out the entire lin clan,
包括林書豪本人
Including the linsational jeremy himself.
我不知道他會來看我的比賽
I did not know he was coming to my game,
我在學校裏確實聽到有人這樣說
And I actually heard from a couple people on campus like,
「嘿，聽說你哥要來」
"hey, your brother's coming."
我的反應是，「不，他不會來的」
I was like, "no, he's not."
從來沒有過
I've never really had that before,
我的一場比賽有那麼大的關注
Had that kind of hype around one of my games.
但我覺得這並沒有很大區別
But I didn't see it as that big of a difference.
不過就是家人來看我的比賽
It was just my family watching my game, so...
在「林瘋狂」之前他就有來看過
I mean, he did come down before linsanity happened.
在那之前，他來看比賽時
He had come down to watch my games before that,
完全沒有人會關心
And no one really cared.
過去兩年
For the last, like, two years,
他在球場上一直鬱鬱不得志
He was never enjoying himself out there.
直到與籃網隊的那場比賽過後
But that new jersey game, when things were rolling,
我第一次覺得，他在享受比賽
For the first time, he was just, like, having fun,
活在自己的夢想之中
Living his dream.
我覺得這才是「林瘋狂」給他帶來的，最美好的東西
I think that was, like, the best thing from linsanity.
現在最重要的問題是：「林瘋狂」能繼續嗎？
The big question now is, can linsanity continue?
我不知道這將持續多久
I don't know how long it's gonna last,
但現在，我不在乎
But right now, I don't care.
林書豪底角嘗試三分
Lin out of the corner for 3.
球進了！
Count 'em all!
如果有人說預料到這一切，那是在瞎說
Anyone who said they saw this coming is lying!
他能做到的遠不止於人們以為的那樣
There's a lot more that he can do
他的信心已經今非昔比
Than anybody knew, and it comes down to confidence.
林書豪突破
Jeremy on the drive.
2+1打成
And-1 for jeremy lin!
打進還造成犯規
He got the bang and the bucket.
他有自己的招牌
He's got that swagger.
他現在很有范兒
He has that "it" right now.
這超越了體育的範疇
This transcends sports. It really does.
他在當今體育界最美妙的故事裏大放光芒
He has shined and evolved into the best story in sports today.
在後場施加壓力
Pressure in the backcourt.
林書豪搶斷，直搗黃龍
Oh, and lin the steal! To the basket!
林書豪面對德克·諾維茨基的防守
Lin, over dirk.
噢噢噢！
Ohh!
太精彩了
How good is this?
我只是想去享受比賽
I'm just out there having fun
打好球
And playing a game.
我會有表現不好的時候
I can have bad games, and, you know,
他們也許會不喜歡我，會噓我
They may not like me, or they may boo me.
但生命中有很多事情遠比籃球重要
There's a lot more important things in life than just basketball.
畢竟籃球只是一場遊戲
'cause at the end of the day, basketball's just a game.
這場秀還在繼續
The show continues on broadway.
這個故事有很多亮點
It's a story with many spokes.
常春藤，美籍亞裔運動員
An ivy leaguer, asian-american athlete,
從替補席橫空出世
Guy off the end of the bench.
為所有沒有得到機會的人代言
Speaks for everyone who didn't get their chance.
只是短短的幾周，在紐約城
It's only a couple of weeks, but in new york city,
在籃球這一大舞台上
And on basketball's big stage,
他已經把故事帶出了籃球這個公園
This guy has hit it out of the park.
在我身上發生的故事
What happened to me, the story that happened to me,
並不是說，我早就知道
I mean, it wasn't like I knew
我能從替補席上來完成那些事情
I could just come off the bench and do that.
我真的不知道
I really didn't.
我覺得自己有這個水平
Um, I thought I could play at this level,
我覺得自己可以成為好的球員
And I thought I could be a good player,
但我沒想到會發生這一系列事情
But I didn't feel like that would happen.
有些球場上的經歷
And some of those experiences out there when I was on the court,
我覺得自己是被別的力量控制著
I felt like I was being controlled by something else.
有些完全超出肉體
I felt like I was having an out-of-body experience.
我完成的一些得分
Some of the plays that I made,
我們的一些勝利
Some of the wins that we had,
真的超出了這個世界
Were just so out of this world
我時常還要掐一下自己
That I still have to pinch myself
才能相信這是真的
To really believe it.
職業生涯前9場首發比賽中
場均9.9次助攻，2.2次搶斷
25.0分
在NBA 65年的歷史中
這個記錄前無古人
他創紀錄式的表現過後
在休賽期成為自由球員
他只收到休斯頓火箭隊的報價
並最終簽下3年2500萬美元的合同
隨著林書豪翻開新的篇章
As jeremy ends one chapter and begins another,
前面的路將不斷地考驗他的毅力
The road ahead will continue to test his perseverance.
他的信念將永遠指引他
But his faith will forever guide him.
去年我學會了
The thing I had to learn last year
完美的計劃並不是
Is a perfect plan doesn't mean
所有的事情都如你所願
That it ends up the way you want it to end up.
如果你之前問我，什麼是完美的計劃
In the past, if you asked me what's a perfect plan,
我可能會答，「心想事成」
I'd be like, "I get what I want,
「打好球，實現夢想」
I get my dream, I play well."
現在我有新的看法
Now I have a different perspective
關於什麼才是完美的計劃
On what a perfect plan is.
如果你一直贏，你不會成長
You don't get better if you win all the time.
只有失敗才會讓你成長
You know, you get better when you lose.
失敗讓你提高
You improve when you lose.
失敗讓你更加反思自我
You look at yourself more when you lose.
如果你我都學到很多
So if you learn a lot or if I learn a lot,
如果我有很好的成長
If I grow a lot,
如果我隨著時間流逝變成更好的人
If I become a better person through tough times,
這才是神的完美計劃的一部分
That's part of his perfect plan.
才是神的完美旨意的一部分
That's part of his perfect will.
如果我感到缺乏安全感
When I was going through all my insecurities
失去信心
And uncertainty and lack of confidence,
那是因為我分散了對神的專注
I was losing focus on god.
我把注意力放到別的事情上了
I was focusing on all these other things,
比如我的工作和別人的想法
Like my job and what other people thought of me
以及各種對我的報道
And what the reporters were writing.
但隨著時間流逝，我會反思自己
You know, over time, I was able to check myself
找回我對神的專注
And kind of get my focus back.
我覺得神對我做了一些超自然的事情
And I think god did something supernatural in me,
一些我無法以一己之力完成的事情
Something that I couldn't do on my own,
有些我也許永遠無法複製
Something that I may never be able to recreate.
所以在那件事上
So I think, in that instance,
我只是學著去奮鬥
I was just learning to fight
去為了神而生活和打球
To constantly live and play for god.
如果我做到這些，我就能完成看似不可能的事情
And when I do that, I'll be able to walk on water.
上面全是《獅子王》的角色
It's all about lion king.
這裏有娜娜
We have nala right here,
還有小辛巴，丁滿和彭彭
Baby simba, timon and pumbaa.
林氏王朝字幕組出品
轉載請註明